<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Erik Reinertsen</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000"/>
 <updated>2019-10-29T16:00:26-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
   <email>erikrtn@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Reviews and opinion pieces on machine learning in healthcare</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/reviews-on-ml-in-healthcare/"/>
   <updated>2019-08-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/reviews-on-ml-in-healthcare</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMra1806949&quot;&gt;Sim, I. Mobile devices and health. NEJM 2019.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/landig/article/PIIS2589-7500(19)30109-8/fulltext&quot;&gt;Snyder M, Zhou W. Big data and health. Lancet 2019.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-019-0148-3&quot;&gt;Shah P, Kendall F, Khozin S, et al. Artificial intelligence and machine learning in clinical development: a translational perspective. npj Digit Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-019-0548-6&quot;&gt;Wiens J, Saria S, Sendak M, et al. Do no harm: a roadmap for responsible machine learning for health care. Nat Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMra18142590&quot;&gt;Rajkomar A, Dean J, Kohane I. Machine Learning in Medicine. N Engl J Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2718456&quot;&gt;Maddox TM, Rumsfeld JS, Payne PRO. Questions for Artificial Intelligence in Health Care. JAMA 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-018-0310-5&quot;&gt;Gottesman O, Johansson F, Komorowski M, et al. Guidelines for reinforcement learning in healthcare. Nat Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-018-0307-0&quot;&gt;He J, Baxter SL, Xu J, Xu J, Zhou X, Zhang K. The practical implementation of artificial intelligence technologies in medicine. Nat Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-018-0316-z&quot;&gt;Esteva A, Robicquet A, Ramsundar B, et al. A guide to deep learning in healthcare. Nat Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2734581&quot;&gt;Emanuel EJ, Wachter RM. Artificial Intelligence in Health Care: Will the Value Match the Hype? JAMA 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-018-0300-7&quot;&gt;Topol EJ. High-performance medicine: the convergence of human and artificial intelligence. Nat Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/landig/article/PIIS2589-7500(19)30084-6/fulltext&quot;&gt;Ghassemi M, Naumann T, Schulam P, Beam AL, Chen IY, Ranganath R. Practical guidance on artificial intelligence for health-care data. Lancet Digit Heal 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(19)30037-6&quot;&gt;Collins GS, Moons KGM. Reporting of artificial intelligence prediction models. Lancet 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-019-0155-4&quot;&gt;Panch T, Mattie H, Celi LA. The “inconvenient truth” about AI in healthcare. npj Digit Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-019-0157-2&quot;&gt;Cahan EM, Hernandez-Boussard T, Thadaney-Israni S, Rubin DL. Putting the data before the algorithm in big data addressing personalized healthcare. npj Digit Med 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://qualitysafety.bmj.com/content/28/3/238.abstract&quot;&gt;Yu KH, Kohane IS. Framing the challenges of artificial intelligence in medicine. BMJ Qual Saf 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/364/bmj.l886&quot;&gt;Watson DS, Krutzinna J, Bruce IN, et al. Clinical applications of machine learning algorithms: Beyond the black box. BMJ 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stm.sciencemag.org/content/10/471/eaao5333.full&quot;&gt;Price NW. Big data and black-box medical algorithms. Science Translational Medicine 2018.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41551-018-0305-z&quot;&gt;Yu KH, Beam AL, Kohane IS. Artificial intelligence in healthcare. Nat Biomed Eng. 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2675024&quot;&gt;Beam AL, Kohane IS. Big Data and Machine Learning in Health Care. JAMA 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2713901&quot;&gt;Shortliffe EH, Sepúlveda MJ. Clinical Decision Support in the Era of Artificial Intelligence. JAMA 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamainternalmedicine/article-abstract/2718342&quot;&gt;Wang F, Casalino LP, Khullar D. Deep Learning in Medicine — Promise, Progress, and Challenges. JAMA Intern Med 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2701665&quot;&gt;Stead WW. Clinical Implications and Challenges of Artificial Intelligence and Deep Learning. JAMA 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2701667&quot;&gt;Naylor CD. On the Prospects for a (Deep) Learning Health Care System. JAMA 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2702879&quot;&gt;Zhu L, Zheng WJ. Informatics, Data Science, and Artificial Intelligence. JAMA 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2703939&quot;&gt;Nsoesie EO. Evaluating Artificial Intelligence Applications in Clinical Settings. JAMA Netw Open 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2701666&quot;&gt;Hinton G. Deep Learning — A Technology With the Potential to Transform Health Care. JAMA 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/10.1056/NEJMp1702071&quot;&gt;Chen J, Ash SM. Machine Learning and Prediction in Medicine — Beyond the Peak of Inflated Expectations. NEJM 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2588761&quot;&gt;Beam AL, Kohane IS. Translating Artificial Intelligence Into Clinical Care. JAMA 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp1606181&quot;&gt;Obermeyer Z, Emanual EJ. Predicting the Future — Big Data, Machine Learning, and Clinical Medicine. NEJM 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.001593&quot;&gt;Deo, R. Machine learning in medicine. Circulation 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to give a great chalk talk</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/give-a-great-chalk-talk/"/>
   <updated>2019-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/give-a-great-chalk-talk</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the medicine sub-internship (“sub-I”) at Emory, we give an 8-15 minute chalk talk on one topic from our curriculum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acute kidney injury&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Edema&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acute respiratory complaints&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GI bleeding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acute diarrhea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abdominal pain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chest pain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HIV + HA or cough&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dyspnea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anemia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bleeding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Syncope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These topics comprise the “Approaches” curriculum designed by the sub-I director Dr. Richard Pittman and are drawn from the textbook &lt;a href=&quot;https://accessmedicine.mhmedical.com/book.aspx?bookid=383&quot;&gt;“Symptom to Diagnosis: An Evidence-Based Guide”&lt;/a&gt;. Topics are organized by a patient’s presenting problem or complaint, rather than diagnosis or organ system. This better reflects diagnostic reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I share thoughts on how to prepare and deliver a great chalk talk, especially in the context of the medicine sub-I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To do: insert photo of example Approaches chalk talk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To do: add short paragraph to emphasize that an incentive to doing this is to develop a repertoire of short teaching scripts to retain through residency, fellowship and beyond.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To do: emphasize the point of Approaches is to build a mental map of how to work through diagnosis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To do: Pipes &amp;amp; Water; emphasize branch points that help separate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To do: reduce number of bullet points below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare&quot;&gt;Prepare&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read your chapter.&lt;/strong&gt; Spend quality time with the material, outline key points with pen and paper, and reflect on one of your patients with said complaint cements the knowledge. This sounds obvious but you really need to know your chapter better than everyone in the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define the scope of the talk.&lt;/strong&gt; This means a subtopic within the chapter. I suggest aiming for 10 minutes because 15 minutes feels long. Your goal is to deliver a “tight” talk which is defined by a stimulating but not overwhelming density of information. Do not underwhelm by oversimplifying or covering too few topics at a slow pace. Typically restraint beats excess, but if your goal is excellence you must hit the sweet spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan how to use your canvas.&lt;/strong&gt; You will be using the whiteboard, not slides and a projector. Sketch it out on paper. Or even better, use a real whiteboard to develop the talk. Avoid crowding or empty spaces. Keep content density balanced. Decide which colors to use for what content, e.g. red for topic names, black for details, and blue for lab values or specific examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organize the information.&lt;/strong&gt; The only way to effectively map complex information from your brain to theirs is to be very organized. As a general rule, one main topic can be branched into 3-5 subtopics, but going broader or deeper in 10 minutes is not recommended. Use diagrams, drawings, mnemonics, or some visualization to give the audience a scaffold upon which to organize what you teach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create an accompanying handout.&lt;/strong&gt; I like handouts that complement the chalk talk. Information on the handout should not be redundant with the whiteboard. Add “fill in the blanks” for key information, e.g. physical exam findings with high positive likelihood ratios in acute MI. Think how you can use the handout to let your audience participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep it clinically relevant.&lt;/strong&gt; Open with why everyone should know what you are about to teach. Effective openers remind us how common or serious the presenting problem is. For example, ask the M4s to imagine being fresh interns and getting paged for acute GI bleeding while on night float. They will now pay extra attention to your neat diagram of management. Bonus points if you incorporate a score on MDCalc that is actually useful, e.g. CURB-65 for your talk on pneumonia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practice.&lt;/strong&gt; Teaching is like everything else in life. Improvement is the result of arduous preparation done intentionally and often. There is no way to skip it. If you practice, especially in front of colleagues or record a video of yourself, you will improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deliver&quot;&gt;Deliver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t preview too much or obsess over learning objectives.&lt;/strong&gt; For a short talk you should be extremely brief with your outline, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Today we will talk about the initial evaluation of a patient with AKI. We’ll focus on the must-not-miss diagnoses of hypovolemia and obstruction, what to focus on in the physical exam, and how to interpret relevant lab tests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write legibly, ahead of time, and with good whiteboard markers.&lt;/strong&gt; Take time to add some content to the whiteboard before you begin. It is very hard to write as fast as you speak, and you will feel slow and start writing too fast, and your handwriting will become illegible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pace should be energetic, yet in control, and never rushed.&lt;/strong&gt; Calibrate your sense of pace by practicing (see above). Don’t bore everyone by speaking too slowly. Don’t run out of time and rush at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be aware of body language.&lt;/strong&gt; Some people pace, wring their hands, or look at the floor. Everyone has a different style and you can make yours work for you. Just be self-aware and adjust PRN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage the audience.&lt;/strong&gt; Even if you did not architect questions into the talk, you can interact as you go. Make eye contact instead of facing the board the entire time. Assess understanding as you go, acknowledge if a colleague had a relevant patient situation to the topic, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finish by summarizing the main ~3 learning points.&lt;/strong&gt; Reinforce what you want people to remember. If you opened with a clinical scenario or case, circle back and close the loop.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Papers on AI in medicine</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/AI-medicine-papers/"/>
   <updated>2018-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/AI-medicine-papers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Organized by application area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anesthesiology&quot;&gt;Anesthesiology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bispec during proprofol + remifentanil: &lt;a href=&quot;http://anesthesiology.pubs.asahq.org/article.aspx?articleid=2656314&quot;&gt;Lee et al. Anesthesiology (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Post-op mortaltiy: &lt;a href=&quot;http://anesthesiology.pubs.asahq.org/article.aspx?articleid=2679105&quot;&gt;Lee et al. Anesthesiology (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hypotension in ICU or OR from a-line: &lt;a href=&quot;http://anesthesiology.pubs.asahq.org/article.aspx?articleid=2685008&quot;&gt;Hatib et al. Anesthesiology (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Postinduction hypotension: &lt;a href=&quot;http://anesthesiology.pubs.asahq.org/article.aspx?articleid=2696388&quot;&gt;Kendale et al. Anesthesiology (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Intraoperative hypoxemia: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41551-018-0304-0&quot;&gt;Lundberg et al. Nature BME (2018)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Identifying high-risk surgical patients: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002701&quot;&gt;Corey et al. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;critical-care&quot;&gt;Critical care&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sepsis in ED triage: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/horng.pdf&quot;&gt;Horng et al. PLoS One (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Septic shock in the ICU: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/henry.pdf&quot;&gt;Henry et al. Sci Trans Med (2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sepsis in ICU: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/nemati.pdf&quot;&gt;Nemati et al. Crit Care Med (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
ICU mortality: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/meiring.pdf&quot;&gt;Meiring et al. PLoS One (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oncology&quot;&gt;Oncology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glioma outcomes: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/mobadersany.pdf&quot;&gt;Mobadersanya et al. PNAS (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mortality s/p cancer chemo: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/elfiky.pdf&quot;&gt;Elfiky et al. JAMA Network Open (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Outcomes in colorectal cancer: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/bychkov.pdf&quot;&gt;Bychkov et al. Sci Reports (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Drug combo for multiple myeloma: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/rashid.pdf&quot;&gt;Rashid et al. Sci Trans Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Skin cancer: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/esteva.pdf&quot;&gt;Esteva et al. Nature (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nonpigmented skin cancer: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/tschandl.pdf&quot;&gt;Tschandl et al. JAMA Derm. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
NSCLC from histopathology: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/coudray.pdf&quot;&gt;Coudray et al. Nature Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Metastatic breast cancer detection: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/liu.pdf&quot;&gt;Liu et al. Arch Pathol Lab Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/steiner.pdf&quot;&gt;Steiner et al. Am J Surg Path (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cardiology&quot;&gt;Cardiology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Echocardiography: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/zhang.pdf&quot;&gt;Zhang et al. Circulation (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Arrhythmia detection &amp;amp; classification: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-018-0268-3&quot;&gt;Hannun et al. Nature Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Atrial fibrillation: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/shashikumar.pdf&quot;&gt;Shashikumar et al. IEEE EMBS (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Myocardial ischemia via angiography: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002693&quot;&gt;Hae et al. PLoS Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
12-lead EKG vs. conventional algo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022073618302292&quot;&gt;Smith et al. J Elec (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;imaging&quot;&gt;Imaging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acute intracranial hemorrhage: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41551-018-0324-9&quot;&gt;Lee et al. Nature BME (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Acute neurological events from head CTs: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/titano.pdf&quot;&gt;Titano et al. Nature Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/chilamkurthy.pdf&quot;&gt;Chilamkurthy et al. Lancet (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mammographic breast density: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/lehman.pdf&quot;&gt;Lehman et al. Radiology (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Diabetic retinopathy (retrospective): &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/defauw.pdf&quot;&gt;De Fauw et al. Nature Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Diabetic retinopathy (prospective pilot): &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/kanagasingam.pdf&quot;&gt;Kanagasingam et al. JAMA Network Open (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Diabetic retinopathy (prospective pilot in primary care offices): &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/abramoff.pdf&quot;&gt;Abramoff et al. npj Dig Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Congenital cataracts (multihospital collaborative platform): &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/long.pdf&quot;&gt;Long et al. Nature BME (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Classifying 14 different pathologies from CXR (CheXNeXt): &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002686&quot;&gt;Rajpurkar et al. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Pneumothorax from CXR: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002697&quot;&gt;Taylor, Mielke, &amp;amp; Mongan. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pneumonia from CXR: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002683&quot;&gt;Zech et al. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Radiology text report classification: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/banerjee.pdf&quot;&gt;Banerjee et al. AI in Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Knee MRI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002699&quot;&gt;Bien et al. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-readmissions-mortality-dx&quot;&gt;General (readmissions, mortality, dx)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readmission: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/shameer.pdf&quot;&gt;Shameer et al. Pacific Symp Biocomp (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Daily risk of C. dif: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/oh.pdf&quot;&gt;Oh et al. Inf Control &amp;amp; Hosp Epi (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dx from EMR data: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/miotto.pdf&quot;&gt;Miotto et al. Sci Reports (2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dx from EMR data: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/yang.pdf&quot;&gt;Yang et al. Sci Reports (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Predict dz onset from lab tests: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1608.00647&quot;&gt;arXiv:1608.00647v3 [cs.LG]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In-hospital mortality, unplanned readmission, prolonged LOS, final discharge dx: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/rajkomar.pdf&quot;&gt;Rajkomar et al. npj Digit Med (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Mortality for palliative care consults: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.06402&quot;&gt;arXiv:1711.06402v1 [cs.CY]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
ED admission from EMR: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002695&quot;&gt;Rahimian et al. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Relationship between IgE to specific allergens and asthma: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002696&quot;&gt;Platts-Mills &amp;amp; Perzanowski. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
AKI after PCI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.1002703&quot;&gt;Huang et al. PLoS Med. (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;neuro--psych&quot;&gt;Neuro &amp;amp; psych&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dementia: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/cleret.pdf&quot;&gt;Cleret et al. JMIR (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Alzheimer’s disease: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/mathotaarachchi.pdf&quot;&gt;Mathotaarachchi et al. Neurobiol Aging (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Suicide: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/walsh.pdf&quot;&gt;Walsh et al. Clin Psych Sci (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Delirium: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/wong.pdf&quot;&gt;Wong et al. JAMA Network Open (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Schizophrenia from HR data: &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/reinertsen.pdf&quot;&gt;Reinertsen et al. Phys Meas (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Schizophrenia from wearables data: &lt;a href=&quot;http://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1361-6579/aae1ed&quot;&gt;Reinertsen et al. Phys Meas (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
PTSD from HR data: &lt;a href=&quot;http://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1361-6579/aa6e9c&quot;&gt;Reinertsen et al. Phys Meas (2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;basic-science&quot;&gt;Basic science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cell counting, detection, &amp;amp; morphometry: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-018-0261-2&quot;&gt;Falk et al. Nature Methods (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Prediction of cancer cell neoantigens from HLA peptide mass spec: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt.4313&quot;&gt;Bulik-Sullivan et al. Nature Biotech (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
GANs for super-resolution microscopy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-018-0239-0&quot;&gt;Wang et al. Nature Methods (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Pre-filled surgical consent forms</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/consents/"/>
   <updated>2018-07-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/consents</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instead of wasting time finding the printed form and filling it out by hand, just print a pre-filled PDF. Now go consent your patient!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/consents/blank.pdf&quot;&gt;Blank form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/consents/abscess.pdf&quot;&gt;Abscess (EUA, I&amp;amp;D)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/consents/appendectomy.pdf&quot;&gt;Appendectomy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/consents/cholecystectomy.pdf&quot;&gt;Cholecystectomy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/consents/peg.pdf&quot;&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note these are Emory Healthcare forms and cannot be used at Grady or other hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My computing setup</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/computing-setup/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/computing-setup</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/setup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/macbook-pro/&quot;&gt;13” Macbook Pro without touchbar&lt;/a&gt;: I tried the touch bar but it was more expensive and less useful than tactile keys.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Dell-Ultrasharp-U2415-24-Inch-LED-Lit/dp/B00NZTKOQI?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;colid=3VQOYNDOY25H&amp;amp;coliid=I39YUWPZNQ483D&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;ref_=wl_it_dp_o_pC_S_ttl&quot;&gt;Dell Ultrasharp U2415 24” monitor&lt;/a&gt; plus a cheap extra HP display I found in the office.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-Ergonomic-Wireless-Desktop-Keyboard/dp/B00CYX54C0/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1500304320&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=microsoft+ergonomic+keyboard+and+mouse&quot;&gt;Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard and mouse&lt;/a&gt;: feels great even after coding and writing for hours.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twelvesouth.com/wallpaper&quot;&gt;Dual-screen wallpapers from TwelveSouth&lt;/a&gt;: I love Hawaii!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Bose-QuietComfort-Wireless-Headphones-Cancelling/dp/B01E3SNO1G&quot;&gt;Bose QuietComfort 35 Wireless Headphones&lt;/a&gt;: great for working in an open office space, and plane flights.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wayfair.com/Steelcase-Airtouch%E2%84%A2-Standing-Desk-SCA1146.html&quot;&gt;SteelSeries Airtouch standing desk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything goes into my Macbook via two USB-C cables. I route all my USB-A peripherals through the Dell monitor, which routes both USB and video to a USB-C hub that also has ethernet and power for the Mac. The hub connects to my Mac via a USB-C extension cable so I can keep the mess hidden under the desk. I use an HDMI to USB-C cable (in red) to connect my Mac to the second display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tip from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/mattmight&quot;&gt;@mattmight&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Buy multiple laptop chargers. Leave one at your office, one at home, etc. It can actually &lt;a href=&quot;http://matt.might.net/articles/artificial-scarcity/&quot;&gt;make economic sense&lt;/a&gt; if the cost of packing up your charger exceeds the cost of buying another one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iterm2.com/&quot;&gt;iTerm2&lt;/a&gt;; much better than the default macOS terminal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mathiasbynens/dotfiles&quot;&gt;Mathias Bynen’s dotfiles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sitepoint.com/getting-started-vim/&quot;&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; to write code; steep learning curve but useful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ethanschoonover.com/solarized&quot;&gt;Solarized&lt;/a&gt; theme.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT207513&quot;&gt;Night Shift&lt;/a&gt; active 24/7 to reduce eye strain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mendeley.com/&quot;&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt; to manage research papers and references. Export &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.bib&lt;/code&gt; files when you write papers, sync your PDFs to the cloud, read and annotate PDFs on any device, and create shared folders with your team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://overleaf.com&quot;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt; for writing papers in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\LaTeX{}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Matlab style guide</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/matlab-style-guide/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/matlab-style-guide</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;People often write unreadable and disorganized code. This is especially true in Matlab, which is used by engineers and scientists who lack formal backgrounds in software development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using consistent and rational style guidelines will help you, colleagues, and any future users of your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clean code is not just for aesthetics. You’ll write faster and think more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a Matlab style guide I’ve found helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;add-spaces-between-arguments&quot;&gt;Add spaces between arguments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a space before each argument.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add spaces before and after &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;myCellArray(i, :) = featureValues;
[outputA, outputB] = myFunction(inputX, inputY);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;myCellArray(i,:)=featureValues;
[outputA,outputB]=myFunction(inputX,inputY);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-a-neat-and-consistent-style-for-comments&quot;&gt;Use a neat and consistent style for comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a space between the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; and the comment text.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capitalize the first letter of each comment sentence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Break up long sentences with newlines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;% This is a comment.
% This is the second line of a comment.
% And also an example of a comment that goes on too long.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;%This is a less readable comment.
%this is the second line of a less readable comment. And also an example of a comment that goes on too long.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;comment-heavily&quot;&gt;Comment heavily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comment each chunk of code that does something useful. Help the reader understand the broad conceptual approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;% Load data from CSV file in Data folder into Matlab
data = loadDataFromCSV(pathToCSV);

% Clean data by removing patients with &amp;lt;50 data points
dataCleaned = cleanData(data);

% Extract features from cleaned data
features = extractFeatures(dataCleaned);

% Initialize arrays to store outputs
idxPatientsToRemove = [];
serumCreatinine = [];
nMedRecords = [];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;indent-your-code&quot;&gt;Indent your code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Python, indentation dictates logic, so you can’t be sloppy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Matlab allows awful indentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorly indented code is hard to follow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;for i=1:10
a = i*rand(1e3);
for j = 5:20
if j &amp;gt; 10 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; a &amp;lt; 50
b(i, j) = a*j;
else
b(i, j) = NaN;
end
end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using tabs makes nested logic more understandable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;for i=1:10
    a = i*rand(1e3);
    for j = 5:20
        if j &amp;gt; 10 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; a &amp;lt; 50
            b(i, j) = a*j;
        else
            b(i, j) = NaN;
        end
    end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;add-space-around-operators-when-performing-math&quot;&gt;Add space around operators when performing math&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line is easy to read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;a = b * c + (i .^ j) / (500 - alpha);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line is harder to read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;a=b*c+(i.^j)/(500-alpha);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also use newlines and indentations to improve readibility of long expressions, especially with fractions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;a = ((b + c) .^ beta) / ...
    (b - x * pi);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-a-consistent-and-structured-header&quot;&gt;Use a consistent and structured header&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The header at the top of your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.m&lt;/code&gt; file should explain the:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Purpose and broad approach of the function&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inputs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outputs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short example of how to call the function is helpful too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/erikrtn/matlabMisc/blob/master/header.m&quot;&gt;this matlab header&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;% [outputVar] = functionName(inputVar)
% 
% Overview
%    Description of function goes here. 
%     
% Input
%    inputVar:
%
% Output
%    outputVar:
%
% Dependencies
%    https://github.com/...
%
% Reference(s)
% 
% Copyright (C) 2017 FIRSTNAME LASTNAME &amp;lt;email@address.com&amp;gt;
% All rights reserved.
%
% This software may be modified &amp;amp; distributed under the terms
% of the BSD license. See LICENSE file in repo for details.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;write-modular-functions-to-organize-code-by-task&quot;&gt;Write modular functions to organize code by task&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pipeline.m&lt;/code&gt; script modularizes major tasks into functions, with clear and self-explanatory variable names, input arguments, and outputs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;function pipeline(pathToCSV)

data = loadDataFromCSV(pathToCSV);
dataCleaned = cleanData(data);
features = extractFeatures(dataCleaned);
[trainingData, testData, trainingLabels, testLabels] = ...
    createCrossValSets(features, labels);
trainWeights = learnWeights(trainingData, trainingLabels);
yHat = predictOutputs(trainWeights, testData);
classifierPerf = assessPerformance(yHat, testLabels);

end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal modularity strikes a balance between depth and breadth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many or too few sub-functions are hard to navigate or delegate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t write the entire codebase of a project in a single file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-mixed-case-for-variable-function-and-file-names&quot;&gt;Use mixed case for variable, function, and file names&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also called “camel capitalization”, this is standard practice for C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first letter is lowercase, and new words are capitalized:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;activityVariance
sepsisScore
nValidScores
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underscores are also popular for variable names, i.e. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;activity_variance&lt;/code&gt;, and works fine too. However, the TeX interpreter in Matlab will read undescores as a switch to subscript. This can be problematic if you label parts of a plot using text derived from variable names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;name-variables-and-functions-by-meaning-or-use&quot;&gt;Name variables and functions by meaning or use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Descriptive variable or function names help people understand how your code works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the person who wrote the code forgets how it works if they step away from it for a few days. So make your code easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functions should be &lt;em&gt;verbs&lt;/em&gt; because functions perform &lt;em&gt;actions&lt;/em&gt; on objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objects should be &lt;em&gt;nouns&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;featuresMatrix = convertFeatStructToMatrix(featuresStruct);
betas = estimateBetas(featuresMatrix, labels);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;m = featuresmatrix(x);
b = betascalc(m, y);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prefix-variables-representing-number-of-items-with-n&quot;&gt;Prefix variables representing number of items with &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nFiles
nSegments
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;suffix-variables-representing-a-single-entity-with-no&quot;&gt;Suffix variables representing a single entity with &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;patientIdNo
hospitalNo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prefix-iterator-variables-with-the-counter-ie-i&quot;&gt;Prefix iterator variables with the counter, i.e. &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;for iPatient = 1:nPatients
    patientIdNo = patientData(iPatient).id;
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-not-use-spaces-for-folder-or-file-names&quot;&gt;Do not use spaces for folder or file names&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matlab and other languages do not handle spaces well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, spaces must be escaped in Unix. If you want to navigate into a directory named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;project results&lt;/code&gt; and view a file named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;beta test values.csv&lt;/code&gt;, you have to type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd project\ results
less beta\ test\ values.csv
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is annoying. Use mixed case or underscores instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd projectResults
less betaTestValues.csv
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple bash script (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/erikrtn/bashscripts/blob/master/replacespaces.sh&quot;&gt;replaceSpaces.sh&lt;/a&gt;) replaces spaces with underscores for all files in the current working directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a more detailed style guide, I recommend &lt;em&gt;MATLAB Programming Style Guidelines&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;www.datatool.com/downloads/matlab_style_guidelines.pdf&quot;&gt;(link to PDF)&lt;/a&gt; by Richard Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hertz Fellowship interview questions</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/hertz-interview/"/>
   <updated>2017-03-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/hertz-interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, I applied for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hertzfoundation.org/dx/fellowships/fellowshipaward.aspx&quot;&gt;Hertz Foundation Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;, and was invited to the first round of interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MD/PhD students are eligible for the Hertz Fellowship, unlike the NSF Graduate Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hertz interviews are technical, and similar to PhD qualifying exams (which I wrote about in &lt;a href=&quot;http://erikreinertsen.com/phd-quals-gtbme/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I describe the questions I was asked and the answers I gave. Each interview covers different topics, some of which are selected by the applicant, so your experience will differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interview questions are block quoted, and my responses are plain text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tell me how your journey started, back when you chose a college, then decided to pursue MD/PhD training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel like writing this out, but same information as was in my essays when I applied to MD/PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why did you switch your interests from biomaterials to software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is eating the world (shoutout to A16Z).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Where do you see yourself after finishing school, then after that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residency, then faculty with joint appointments in medicine and engineering. I want to balance patient care, research, and teaching in a synergistic fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds cliched, but interestingly it is also one of the rarest outcomes for any academic doctor. Everyone says they want to do it because they think the admissions committees want to hear it. They may be right. Lots of us say this because we truly want to do it. But the actual number of MDs and MD/PhDs who successfully attain synergy between three very demanding and sometimes conflicting endeavors is small - based on my anecdotal experiences with faculty over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This interview was a while ago and my interests have evolved. These days I am considering non-academic careers.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tell me about a situation in which you exercised creativity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talked about my senior design project at UCLA where we attempted to reduce cell death in polymer scaffolds by seeding cells in a gradient to better control oxygen consumption and diffusion. Our team was limited to 1 or 2-dimensional modeling in COMSOL because of mathematical complexity. To match computational and experimental paradigms, we fabricated polymer discs that fit exactly in the wells of a 48-well plate. Like stacking pancakes of different chocolate chip densities, we stacked discs with different cell densities to crudely control cell distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Another thing Hertz looks for is technical skill. What are some areas we can talk about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chemical engineering, transport, biology / physiology, statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We play a game where I have 1000 coins and you have 1000 coins. We take turns flipping one coin at a time. If it lands heads, I get the coin (or keep it if it was my flip). If it lands tails, you get it. What does the sample space of game outcomes look like? How would you determine the length of the game?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would write some very simple code and run a Monte Carlo simulation, then plot a histogram of outcomes against simulation number. I would expect to see the distribution of game outcome follow a normal distribution if sufficient samples were taken. At this point I cited the central limit theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is an analogous process to this coin-flipping game? What would both the game and the analogous process look like at infinite time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not immediately answer correctly, but we ended up discussing diffusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is the relationship between length scale and diffusion, and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stokes-Einstein equation can be used to relate time scale Tau, length scale lambda, and diffusivity D&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tau = (lambda)^2 / D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above expression is correct for 2D or 3D space. I incorrectly thought it solely applied to 3D space, which was the scenario in which I derived it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Switching gears - how would you construct a biological circuit that can perform logical operations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would introduce two receptors on the surface of a cell that had specific binding to two different ligands; say, calcium versus a neurotransmitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In real life what do the kinetics of ligands binding to a receptor look like, and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the response looks like sigmoidal curve, because of allosteric effects, e.g. hemoglobin. Activity reaches an asymptote. There is also lots of noise in biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How would you make a sigmoidal curve sharper?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I thought to increase the binding affinity of the ligand for the receptor, but that would probably just increase binding at all concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I thought about how hemoglobin works; you could make the receptor or enzyme decrease activity at higher concentrations of ligand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way is to add a 3rd party allosteric modulator, so I used 2,3-BPG acting on hemoglobin as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let us suppose you construct a surface receptor system that lets you signal 1 or 0 using two separate ligand inputs. How would you build an ‘AND’ and an ‘OR’ gate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a downstream signaling integrator, or traffic the signal to a different part of the cell, a la trafficking motifs. I also talked about a very superficial neural network approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Describe an organ system from a clinical perspective, then contrast that to an engineering or science view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain; neurologists think of disease in terms of clinical symptoms or vascular localization. Neuroscientists think about a more microscopic scale, drawing on graph / information theory, electrophysiology, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the heart; physiologists clasically think of CV systems as a network of resistors, capacitors, and pumps (I cited Guyton). Cardiologists integrate a lot of physiology: clots to the brain from atrial fib, or fluid overload hitting the lungs, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, cardiology was a bad example because that is a fairly quantitative medical specialty. But I summarized by saying the major difference between the two views was a quantitative approach, or for a bench scientist, length scale versus clinical integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You mentioned in your application you enjoy cooking. Give me an example of chemical engineering or chemistry in cooking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talked about heat transport in making the perfect filet mignon. Pink in the middle, but seared with a beautiful crust on the outside. You have to use high, intense heat in the beginning to lock in the color and flavor (Maillard reaction), then reduce heat to gently cook the center of the meat further from the heat source. If you want more even diffusion, you can sear on the stovetop and transfer to a convection oven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Outside of your research, what are the three big-picture problems you want to work on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instill rigorous management practices into academia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apply behavioral economics and psychology so society chooses truly impactful problems to work on instead of problems people think are important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use technology in a broad sense (mobile, cloud, analytics) to radically transform training and education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked my interviewer two questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why do you contribute to / get out of Hertz?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He likes meeting and interviewing fellows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What do you strongly believe in that most people disagree with you about?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global health requires technology innovation, but also cultural and policy approaches. People tend to lie in one camp or the other and criticize work outside of their view. I disagree with both extremists and believe we need a combined approach to improve healthcare in underresourced environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I answered the questions well, but was not invited for a final interview. The rest of my application (GPA, publication record, etc.) was probably not as strong as the competition. Congratulations to the brilliant people who won the fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I learned this and much more from &lt;a href=&quot;http://kameilab.seas.ucla.edu/daniel-kamei.html&quot;&gt;Daniel Kamei&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite professors at UCLA. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is (purportedly) Peter Thiel’s favorite interview question. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Remove Microsoft Error Reporting from macOS</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/remove-office-error-reporting/"/>
   <updated>2017-01-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/remove-office-error-reporting</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you force-quit any Microsoft Office application on macOS using Option-Command-Esc, this annoying and useless error reporter
launches:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mer.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Microsoft Error Reporting app exists within &lt;em&gt;each&lt;/em&gt; Office app installed on your Mac, i.e. within Word, OneNote,
PowerPoint, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is insane, so let’s remove it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open terminal and type in the following to delete:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo rm -rf /Applications/Microsoft\ *.app/Contents/SharedSupport/Microsoft\ Error\ Reporting.app/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will go through &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/Microsoft\ Excel.app&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/Microsoft\ PowerPoint.app&lt;/code&gt;, etc. and delete the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be extremely careful using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rm&lt;/code&gt;. Don’t wreck your system.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Forge merger with Sling Health</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/forge-merger-sling-health/"/>
   <updated>2016-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/forge-merger-sling-health</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My team and I are excited to announce that Forge has merged with &lt;a href=&quot;http://slinghealth.org/&quot;&gt;Sling Health&lt;/a&gt; (previously IDEA Labs) — a biomedical design and entrepreneurship incubator with chapters in St. Louis, Boston, Philadelphia, Ann Arbor, and New Orleans. Sling Health collaborates with the American Medical Association and many industry and academic sponsors. Forge is now the Atlanta chapter of Sling Health, and has adopted the latter organization’s branding and vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, Forge helped digital health startups launch pilots with clinical partners in Atlanta. Now, we’ve shifted our focus to ideation stage. Sling Health forms teams of medical, engineering, and business students with mentorship from faculty, clinicians, and local entrepreneurs. The goal is to start companies that solve problems in care delivery or clinical medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help teams do this, Sling Health provides technical, clinical, business, and legal mentorship, initial funding and facilities for prototypes, and legal support. Teams retain 100% of their IP and equity. Since 2014, Sling Health has spent $80,000 to support 133 students. This effort has yielded 16 provisional patents, 12 companies, and $3M in follow-on investment. Sling Health also hosts a national demo day every year for teams from all chapters to present to early-stage investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sling Health’s scope also includes medical devices, expanding Forge’s previous focuson digital health. This vertical is well-represented in Atlanta, with St. Jude’s acquisition of CardioMems, preclinical testing facilities at GCMI, and related research at every engineering department at Georgia Tech (which all rank in the top ten nationally).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Forge team has transitioned to other endeavors. Saumya Venkatesan, a former Forge team member and Georgia Tech alumna, will be leading the new Atlanta chapter of Sling Health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sling Health will create opportunities for innovators at Emory and Georgia Tech. In turn, the outstanding technical, clinical, and entrepreneurial talent in Atlanta will contribute to the broader organization. We invite you to visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://slinghealth.org/&quot;&gt;slinghealth.org&lt;/a&gt; and improve healthcare through technology.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Calling Python 3 in Matlab</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/python3-in-matlab/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/python3-in-matlab</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here I describe three steps to enable calling Python 3 in Matlab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update Matlab path to system path.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automate path addition to run every time Matlab starts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update default version of Python interpreter in Matlab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is the Matlab environment, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; is the Bash shell, and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is the Python environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-update-matlab-path-to-system-path&quot;&gt;1. Update Matlab path to system path&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a system call to python from within the Matlab IDE:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; !python
Python 2.7.10 (default, Oct 23 2015, 19:19:21) 
[GCC 4.2.1 Compatible Apple LLVM 7.0.0 (clang-700.0.59.5)] on darwin
Type &quot;help&quot;, &quot;copyright&quot;, &quot;credits&quot; or &quot;license&quot; for more information.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, macOS defaults &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; calls to Python 2; Python 3 must be explicitly called:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; !python3
/bin/Bash: python3: command not found
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uh oh! Matlab does not source your Bash shell resource file. Even though my Bash shell can handle a call to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python3&lt;/code&gt;, Matlab cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Matlab, my system PATH is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; unix('echo $PATH')
/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/sbin
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Bash, my system PATH is different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ echo $PATH
/Users/erik/bin:/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/sbin:/opt/X11/bin:/Users/erik/.rvm/bin
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to update Matlab’s PATH using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;setenv&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I grab my system PATH onto the clipboard so I can paste it later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ echo $PATH | pbcopy
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, in Matlab I call &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;setenv&lt;/code&gt; and copy my system PATH into the second argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; setenv('PATH', '/Users/erik/bin:/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/sbin:/opt/X11/bin:/Users/erik/.rvm/bin')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now system calls to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python3&lt;/code&gt; work from within Matlab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; !python3
Python 3.5.2 (default, Jul 28 2016, 21:28:00) 
[GCC 4.2.1 Compatible Apple LLVM 7.3.0 (clang-703.0.31)] on darwin
Type &quot;help&quot;, &quot;copyright&quot;, &quot;credits&quot; or &quot;license&quot; for more information.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this situation only lasts for the current Matlab instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-automate-path-addition-to-run-every-time-matlab-starts&quot;&gt;2. Automate path addition to run every time Matlab starts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the addition of the correct path effectively permament, you can add the above code to a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;startup.m&lt;/code&gt; file &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathworks.com/help/matlab/ref/startup.html&quot;&gt;(read more about this here)&lt;/a&gt;. Store it anywhere in the Matlab search path. The script runs every time Matlab is started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the relevant contents of  my &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;startup.m&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;% Add my GitHub repos to search path
addpath(genpath('~/repos'));

% Set OS path for this shell instance
setenv('PATH', '/Users/erik/bin:/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/sbin:/opt/X11/bin:/Users/erik/.rvm/bin');
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally Matlab would automatically import the system PATH, but unfortunately it does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-update-default-version-of-python-interpreter-in-matlab&quot;&gt;3. Update default version of Python interpreter in Matlab&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you want to call Python modules within Matlab, you need to change the default version of the Python interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you check the version loaded in Matlab, you probably see the macOS default version and executable path to that version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; pyversion

       version: '2.7'
    executable: '/usr/bin/python'
       library: '/System/Library/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/2.7/lib/libpython2.7.d…'
          home: '/System/Library/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/2.7'
      isloaded: 0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Python 3 from Bash and find the path to the executable. If you installed Python 3 using Homebrew, your path probably looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; import sys
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(sys.executable)
/usr/local/opt/python3/bin/python3.6
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Matlab and use the path as the argument for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyversion&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; pyversion('/usr/local/opt/python3/bin/python3.6');
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check that your setting of the new executable path worked by calling &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyversion&lt;/code&gt; with no arguments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; pyversion

       version: '3.6'
    executable: '/usr/local/opt/python3/bin/python3.6'
       library: '/usr/local/Cellar/python3/3.6.0/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/3.6/li…'
          home: '/usr/local/Cellar/python3/3.6.0/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/3.6'
      isloaded: 0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have Python 3 goodness within Matlab.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Uber flat fare math</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/uber-flat-fare/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/uber-flat-fare</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Uber is offering &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uber.com/info/plus/sanfrancisco&quot;&gt;$2 flat fares&lt;/a&gt; in San Francisco for September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this a good deal? In other words, if you take uberPOOL, how many flat fare rides does it take to &lt;strong&gt;break even&lt;/strong&gt; with regular uberPOOL?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this simple model, we set the price of regular uberPOOL rides (left side of equation) equal to the price of flat fare uberPOOL rides (right side of equation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical ride price for regular uberPOOL rides is &lt;em&gt;MRP&lt;/em&gt;, the number of rides is &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;, and we assume we only pay for the $20 upfront fee which enables a $2/ride flat fare (up to 20 rides max).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ubermath.png&quot; alt=&quot;ubermath&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can plot &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; versus &lt;em&gt;MRP&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/uberplot.png&quot; alt=&quot;uberplot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note we round the number of rides up to an integer value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine if the new flat fare is a good deal, estimate your typical ride price for uberPOOL, then check how many rides you’d need to take to at least break even. If you take more rides than that, flat fare makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take fewer than &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; rides, you are not taking advantage of the flat fare’s cheaper cost per ride. Given the $20 upfront fee, you should stick with regular uberPOOL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, my typical uberPOOL rides cost about $6. Flat fares are therefore cost-effective if I take 5+ rides that month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take longer (and thus more expensive) uberPOOL rides, e.g. Sunset to FiDi, the savings from flat fare are even greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This same model applies to other cities, or for UberX. Just adjust the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, flat fares are only good for specific times, cities, and regions within those cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovative payment structures like flat fares will help more people afford transportation. Kudos to Uber!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tips for TAing</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/tips-for-taing/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/tips-for-taing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just finished my second and final semester TAing computational systems biology at Georgia Tech. I had fun and I think I did &lt;a href=&quot;http://erikreinertsen.com/teaching/&quot;&gt;well&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I’ll share some thoughts and tips for new TAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pros-and-cons-of-taing&quot;&gt;Pros and cons of TAing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teaching is time-consuming but deepens your understanding of the topic and improves communication skills. If you want to stay in academia or education, TAing is good (and sometimes the only) practice for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You usually&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; get a small pay raise via a “teaching fellowship”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grading problem sets and exams feels like a waste of time and talent, but until education catches up with technology, someone must do it. At least you save your professor some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed hosting small group sessions, holding office hours, and lecturing. You have some agency over your scope, so discuss that interest with your professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing-a-course-to-ta&quot;&gt;Choosing a course to TA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TAing for your advisor seems optimal. You already have a working relationship, and you already should or will have a background in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of who you TA for, choose a course in which you are proficient, or are willing to put in time to learn much about. The students deserve a competent TA and the course will consume less of your time if you’ve already taken (and aced) the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expertise aside, choose a course and a professor you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have the option, co-TA with a colleague you trust&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communicating-with-students&quot;&gt;Communicating with students&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity is key. You are now a source of authority to the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students like when you explain concepts using analogies. They also like concrete examples to solidify abstract concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplify but do not dumb down. There is a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be authentic and real. If you don’t know the answer to a question, say so and don’t bullshit. Find the answer and follow up later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be consistent. Grade everyone the same way. No favors - be professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reply quickly to emails, and be precise with your language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set boundaries on your time. Be firm about the time and place of your office hours, but make yourself more available prior to exams. In other words, match supply and demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked students to schedule office hours with me ahead of time via email. Articulating their question beforehand forced them to think, and sometimes would eliminate the need to meet. If the need to meet remained, it allowed me to prepare so we used our time productively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, asking students to schedule office hours has a downside, as they may feel you are less accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grading&quot;&gt;Grading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Split up the work fairly among co-TAs and rotate responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set your own deadlines when possible, and always meet them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regrades are annoying, but you must fix your mistakes. TAs owe their students fair and correct grading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, don’t let students nitpick for points (usually premeds). Your time is better spent with students who suffered more substantial grading mistakes, or students with a genuine interest in the course material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My program requires all PhD students to TA for two semesters. We are not paid and have little flexibility over which course we TA. I could not even TA my advisor’s course because it was listed uder CS. My instructors were great, but clearly this TA setup is suboptimal. Your teaching experience will vary by institution. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I did not conspire to co-TA my courses with a close colleague. But I was lucky to work with co-TAs who went above and beyond for our team and our students. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Forge progress and next steps</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/forge-progress-next-steps/"/>
   <updated>2016-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/forge-progress-next-steps</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The following is a repost from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forgehealth.org/2016/04/founders-forum-recap-next-steps/&quot;&gt;Forge blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January we accepted four digital health startups to Founders Forum (&lt;a href=&quot;http://forgehealth.org/2016/01/founders-forum-first-cohort/&quot;&gt;see blog post&lt;/a&gt;. This three-month program helped startups launch a clinical or enterprise pilot at Emory or the VA. We also provided $5,000 of grant funding, office space, mentorship, and introductions to enterprise stakeholders. At the end, founders pitched at a demo day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I describe what our startups did and what Forge is doing next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-our-startups-accomplish&quot;&gt;What did our startups accomplish?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We connected founders with physicians and enterprise leaders from Emory Healthcare, Grady Health System, and the Atlanta VA.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our startups now have clinical and operational pilots underway.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving Analytics and the VA Cardiology Division secured a $50,000 grant from the VA Center for Innovation to fund a pilot for home-based cardiac rehab.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fraudscope recruited a senior Emory faculty member and Forge mentor as a Co-Founder and Chief Medical Officer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emory MBA students helped our founders develop go-to-market strategies, perform market research, and revise pitch decks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our startups collectively raised $1M+ in seed capital since Founders Forum ended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-forge-doing-next&quot;&gt;What is Forge doing next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forge, our partners, and our startups are encouraged by these indicators of early success, although other important metrics will take time to assess. Founders Forum was a pilot too, and we liked the results. Moving forward, the work we did through Founders Forum will be what Forge does as an organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our focus remains on digital health, and the vision remains constant: to help fully committed, technical founders solve unmet needs in healthcare. Forge will still hold events like Salons and Meetups; you may see some of our founder alumni join us as speakers and panelists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are evolving our leadership team too. Arash Harzand has stepped up to lead Forge as our CEO, and I am transitioning to an advisory role. To expand our capacity, Forge is hiring a full time Program Manager to lead operations. The team also is creating opportunities for volunteers. Finally, we will grow our network of clinical and technical faculty to serve as study investigators and mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud of what everyone accomplished, but Atlanta’s digital health ecosystem is still nascent. We must do more to help startups raise capital. We can create educational opportunities for students and clinical trainees. We should promote inclusiveness and diversity. Finally, we need to build a culture of paying it forward, which happens when successful founders invest time and capital in new entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founders, clinicians, and volunteers who want to improve healthcare through technology should keep an eye on forgehealth.org for ways to get involved. I’m excited to see Forge and our partners put Atlanta on the map for digital health. The best is yet to come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erik Reinertsen&lt;br /&gt;
Co-founder, Forge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Shawna Hagen, Cory Woodyatt, &amp;amp; Arash Harzand for reading drafts of this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Make $43,000 by not paying your medical school debt</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/roth/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/roth</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During residency, it is economically advantageous to maximize your investment in a Roth IRA versus reducing your interest burden by paying off an equivalent amount of medical school debt. How much better? For each dollar you shift to a Roth IRA, you could be eight dollars better off in the long run. Contribute $15,000 while your income is low and it could be worth $120,000 or more when you retire. Here I will explain why the Roth IRA is a good financial decision for young doctors-in-training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-roth-ira&quot;&gt;What is a Roth IRA?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Roth IRA is retirement plan for people who don’t make much money. You can deposit up to $5,500 per year of earned income. Your maximum deposit limit goes down quickly once your income exceeds $116,000 (i.e. attending-level salary). It is pretty likely that the only time in your life you will be able to exploit the benefits of a Roth IRA is before you complete your residency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roth IRAs have a wide range of investment choices, but the best long term returns are likely to come from investments in equities (stocks), mutual funds, and ETFs. Because the earnings in such an account are reinvested, they compound until you retire and your investment can grow a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, your ultimate withdrawal of money from a Roth IRA is tax-free. In contrast, your withdrawals from a regular IRA will be taxed as ordinary income at a combined state and federal rate, which approaches 50%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-a-roth-ira-good-for-resident-physicians&quot;&gt;Why is a Roth IRA good for resident physicians?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because their income is low enough to qualify and high enough to make the maximum contribution. Because of its tax-free treatment, the eventual returns on the Roth IRA are high enough to more than outweigh extra interest you will pay if you delay paying back your medical school loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, you will end up with &lt;em&gt;much more money&lt;/em&gt; if you contribute modestly to a Roth IRA during residency instead of repaying loans with that cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sounds-too-good-to-be-true-show-me-the-numbers&quot;&gt;Sounds too good to be true. Show me the numbers.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s walk through an example. Say you save up $10,000 over 5 years. Let’s divide that money into two $5,000 investments. The first investment is today and the second investment is 5 years from now, when you are no longer eligible to put money in a Roth IRA. Remember, when you finish residency, your attending-level income makes you ineligible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s make some reasonable assumptions:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Interest rate on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aamc.org/advocacy/meded/79232/federal_student_loans.html&quot;&gt;medical school loan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/042415/what-average-annual-return-sp-500.asp&quot;&gt;Annual market return&lt;/a&gt; on investments&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tax rate on money withdrawn from Roth IRA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tax rate on money withdrawn from regular IRA/401K&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Age at start of residency&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Age at retirement&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two options for our $10,000 of savings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deposit the first $5,000 in a Roth IRA today, and 5 years later use the second $5,000 to repay part of your loan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the first $5,000 to repay part of your loan today, and 5 years later deposit the second $5,000 in your regular IRA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pursue option 1 and compound a $5,000 investment in your Roth IRA by 7% annually for 39 years, you could withdraw $69,974.10 when you retire. The net value of option 1 is therefore $69,974.10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, option 1 postpones repaying $5,000 of your loan for 5 years. This loan accrues $1,691.13 of interest during this period. Such interest could be avoided by paying $5,000 toward the loan on day 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pursue option 2, by paying $5,000 of your loan you save $1,691.13, which is the interest that would have accrued if you pursued option 1. At year 5 you invest the second $5,000 into a regular IRA. This investment compounds for 34 years (39-5) to a total of $49,890.57. Withdrawals from regular IRAs are taxable (~50%) so you end up with $24,945.28. Therefore the net value of option 2 is therefore $1,691.13 + $24,945.28 = $26,636.41.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of option 1 minus the value of option 2 equals &lt;strong&gt;$43,337.69&lt;/strong&gt;. Stated another way every dollar you diverted into your Roth IRA is worth $8 in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/rothira.xls&quot;&gt;Download the spreadsheet here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; You can make different assumptions about tax rate and investment returns and see how this changes the payoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;limitations&quot;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In real life, it is hard to save $5,000 a year. And when your income finally rises it is easy to convince yourself you deserve some long-deferred luxuries. Putting money away in a retirement seems even stranger to a medical student who is facing immense debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average amount of debt US medical students graduate with is $176,000 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aamc.org/download/296002/data/aibvol12_no2.pdf&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). This includes nearly $58,500 in interest charges over the life of the loan. If the physician repays this debt over 10 years, they would pay $1,954 every month. Now add rent, food, taxes, and other costs of living. Quite a challenge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the Roth IRA is a good choice whether you can save $5,000 or only $100. It is hard to beat decades of compounded gains that can be harvested tax free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is economically superior to contribute money every year during residency to your Roth IRA, instead of using the same money to accelerate repayment of your loans. The penalty you pay in extra interest is far lower than the gains you get by exploiting the special tax-free treatment of the Roth account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your total contribution to a Roth IRA reached $15,000 this could be worth an extra $120,000 in the long run. That’s significant enough to impact other goals like a home mortgage, dream vacation, or child’s college education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this discussion is to raise your awareness of this issue. Just the way you get your medical advice from a professional, you should get your tax, legal, investment, and accounting advice from professionals, not from me. What I hope to do is encourage you to ask the right questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In our model, returns after year 5 are identical. This means one key driver of the different outcomes is the extra money you have in your Roth IRA account at start of year 5. This produces a significant benefit for the Roth IRA under any assumed non-negative long-term rate of return. The second driver of the difference is paying taxes on your regular IRA withdrawals. This produces an equally significant advantage for the Roth IRA under virtually any tax rate assumption including the lowest federal tax bracket of 10% for families earning less than $18,450. In summary, the Roth strategy is dominant. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our return assumption is deliberately low to withstand scrutiny. When you are making a judgment regarding returns over a 35 to 40 year period you always need to use long-term data. One of the classic sources for this information is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aaii.com/journal/article/historical-performance-and-future-stock-marketreturn-uncertainties.touch&quot;&gt;Ibbotson&lt;/a&gt; (80+ years). History suggests 10% is a defensible rate, and the 7% we chose is conservative by any measure. Remember, the 1926 - 2009 period in the Ibbotson study included the Great Depression and the recent Great Recession. It is not a cherry-picked period of high returns. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DReinertsen&quot;&gt;@dreinertsen&lt;/a&gt; for making the spreadsheet, providing substantial revisions to this post, and elaborating on assumptions behind the model. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Leadership lessons from the Dean of Stanford Medicine</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/leadership-lessons-from-stanford-med/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/leadership-lessons-from-stanford-med</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the privilege of attending a masterclass on leadership at Stanford University School of Medicine with Lloyd Minor, the Dean. Here’s what we learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/minor1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dean Minor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;photo credit &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/StevenChanMD&quot;&gt;@StevenChanMD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He suggested three readings to prepare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/masterclass_gardner.pdf&quot;&gt;Personal renewal&lt;/a&gt; by John Gardner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/masterclass_kotter.pdf&quot;&gt;What leaders really do&lt;/a&gt; by John Kotter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/masterclass_simmons.pdf&quot;&gt;I was impossible, but then I saw how to lead&lt;/a&gt; by Ruth Simmons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our class had ~15 clinicians, technologists, and students. We started with introductions and then discussed five principles of leadership:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listen &amp;amp; learn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diverse teams maximize performance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empower your team&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:footnote1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:footnote1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Management deals with complexity, while leadership deals with change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan transitions&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:footnote2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:footnote2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Minor also answered some questions from our group:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you earn loyalty, especially when you are a new leader at an established organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buy-in from people you lead is dynamic and evolves over time. Listen and learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you build a culture where people are proud to be part of your organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hire people who already bought in to your vision. People at Stanford or Google &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What do you do if your organization faces a threat and you have to act before getting everyone’s permission?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicate the threat to your organization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protect your organization and make it clear your actions were to do so and not to further your own interest or harm anyone you lead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you create core values in your organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Core values already exist in large orgs; you don’t create them. You have to listen to find, gain consensus around, clarify, and articulate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How do you continue learning leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read (form a group), get a coach, and obtain feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emory should hold similar sessions with our Deans and Chairs to teach students and trainees more about leadership. Stay tuned, I’ll work on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course I had to get a picture with the boss!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/minor2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;selfie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:footnote1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;People should be great solo, but even more amazing together. And don’t restrict the independence of amazing people. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:footnote1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:footnote2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Let everyone know you have arrived to serve them, not yourself. And if you leave, make sure the organization endures. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:footnote2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The PhD qualifying exam at GT BME</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/gtbme-quals/"/>
   <updated>2015-05-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/gtbme-quals</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here I describe my PhD qualifying exam &lt;a href=&quot;#format&quot;&gt;format&lt;/a&gt;, list &lt;a href=&quot;#questions&quot;&gt;questions&lt;/a&gt; I was asked, and offer &lt;a href=&quot;#suggestions&quot;&gt;suggestions&lt;/a&gt;. Note this is n=1 from a single institution and major (Georgia Tech Biomedical Engineering). Also note that BME encompasses many sub-fields, and the qualifying exam is tailored for a specific individual’s coursework and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;format&quot;&gt;Format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GT BME quals are 2-hour oral exams led by a faculty committee.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My committee consisted of one committee chair and two committee members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My advisor quietly &amp;amp; painfully observed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the real questions, I was asked to introduce myself and my research in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the three lines of questioning I experienced. Note you won’t gain anything by preparing to answer these specific questions. Everyone experiences different questions. The purpose of sharing these questions is to help you assess the overall difficulty of the exam and understand how the line of questioning evolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explain what happens electrically when your heart beats.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Draw the ECG waveform.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Explain how the ECG records electrical activity from the heart.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Write an algorithm to determine heart rate from ECG data in real-time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What is the appropriate frequency to measure the QRS complex?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Describe a different way of doing q1.3.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How do you accomplish q1.3. in the presence of noise?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tell me what you know about active transport of cargo inside of a cell.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Describe the forces involved, conceptually and mathematically.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What happens to the complex in the presence of charged molecules?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vesicles actually connect to the dynein-kinesin complex via a tether. How does this tether change your model?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why is experimental design important?
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How many subjects do you need to do an experiment?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Describe beta in the power calculation.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What is the definition of false negative?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;suggestions&quot;&gt;Suggestions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know fundamental topics in your field. I studied cardiac physiology, Nyquist theorem, Fourier transform, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practice answering questions in front of a group. The questions are not too technically complex. The challenge lies in not knowing specific questions in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the whiteboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After you are asked a question, summarize and repeat the question to ensure clarity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you finish answering, summarize your long answer in a short sentence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pause occasionally to solicit feedback from the committee.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not stress out. Just prepare. Enjoy the fact that preparation contributes to your knowledge in your field of research. Most faculty want you succeed. Their goal is not to kick you out or humiliate you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tips for writing your medical school personal statement</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/tips-for-medical-school-ps/"/>
   <updated>2015-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/tips-for-medical-school-ps</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your medical school personal statement (PS) explains why you want to be a physician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An average PS says “I want to be a physician because of X, Y, and Z”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better PS shares a fascinating life story that leaves the reader with one conclusion - your inevitable career in medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a PS is difficult because it demands introspection and brevity. Most people are neither introspective nor brief, but you can improve these traits with practice. Here are some tips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;contents&quot;&gt;Contents:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#brainstorming&quot;&gt;Brainstorming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#writing&quot;&gt;Writing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#writing&quot;&gt;Revising&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dos&quot;&gt;Do’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#donts&quot;&gt;Dont’s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brainstorming&quot;&gt;Brainstorming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explore many concepts and use a blank sheet of paper or post-it notes to reminisce. Write down every person, place, thing, event, or concept that felt important and memorable. Be broad and do not erase anything even if you want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you get started, think about these questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who are your role models and why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What made you curious about science, biology, math, physics, etc.?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What were your proudest or scariest moments in life?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Describe an experience with sickness or injury.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What excites you?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are you GREAT at?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, organize your raw material into &lt;strong&gt;groups&lt;/strong&gt; based on theme or time. Each group should have a one-sentence summary. For example, one group could be “my summer experience building water storage infrastructure in Guatemala”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, gather 3-5 related groups into a &lt;strong&gt;family&lt;/strong&gt;. Each family is a potential essay with one thesis sentence that links the summaries of the groups. A thesis might be “a lifelong passion to improve society through technology”. Groups within this family could include volunteer experiences, or aspects of service and leadership in your research or clinical experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explore several essay ideas and see what tells your story best. Go with your gut. Write a story that is authentically “you”. This makes a more interesting story than guessing what admissions committees want to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing&quot;&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select one &lt;strong&gt;family&lt;/strong&gt; from your brainstorm, then flesh it out with full sentences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just tell your story. It is acceptable to write “stream of consciousness” because you’ll revise later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set aside time to write, then double that time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google Docs will let you collaborate in real-time with mentors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hemingwayapp.com/&quot;&gt;Hemingway editor&lt;/a&gt; to aid brevity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;revising&quot;&gt;Revising&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Print your essay and attack it with a red pen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get feedback from different mentors and peers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track changes is nice but not required. Sometimes it is easier to read a revised essay without the red strikeouts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Step away from your essay and revisit it a day later. You’ll be surprised at how different it reads.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplify your writing. Say the same thing with fewer words.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vary sentence length and structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dos&quot;&gt;Do’s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start your PS in March so you can submit in June.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep it simple, brief, and organized.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transition between ideas and paragraphs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quantify achievements (“I raised $50,000 for my nonprofit organization”).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engage the reader’s emotion through sharing experiences that were emotional to you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perfect is the enemy of done. Submit your primary in June. The marginal benefit from polishing your essay is not worth the cost of applying late.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;donts&quot;&gt;Dont’s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t embellish your essay with complex sentences and fancy vocabulary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t start every sentence with “I…”. Add variety.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t follow every suggestion from your essay reviewers. This is YOUR essay. Their feedback eventually conflicts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t lie or exaggerate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t re-phrase everything on your AMCAS or CV. This is your chance to tell a story, not list awards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t write the same cliché that every other premed writes, i.e. “My parents were doctors, I volunteered in Africa, ran a few gels in a lab, and now want to go to medical school.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Why we started Forge</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/why-we-started-forge/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/why-we-started-forge</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was the first blog post published on Forge’s website, which is now archived here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am excited to kick off 2015 with a blog post describing Forge’s story, principles, and vision of improving healthcare through technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rewind to 2013: as a medical student interested in building new ways to help patients, I was not alone in Atlanta. My colleagues and I enjoyed meeting with residents, faculty, and young professionals to discuss technology in medicine. Our gatherings were informal; we talked about unmet clinical needs, problems with the EMR, and research questions over coffee or brunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One afternoon, a group of Biomedical Engineering students from Georgia Tech approached us. The engineers were starting their semester-long senior projects, and wanted to meet clinicians for input. We offered to host a meeting, but realized we could scale these interactions more. In October 2013, my colleagues and I organized “&lt;a href=&quot;http://forgehealth.org/reports/2013med20.pdf&quot;&gt;Medicine 2.0&lt;/a&gt;”, the first multidisciplinary brainstorming session at Emory University School of Medicine connecting clinicians with engineers and students from Georgia Tech. Medicine 2.0 was one of many gatherings in 2013 that revealed significant interest at Emory and Tech in applying engineering and technology towards medicine in an applied rather than academic fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hypothesized there was a nascent community of clinically-minded technologists andtech-enthused clinicians in Atlanta who wanted to interact but had not found good ways to do so. To learn more about this ecosystem, we joined an executive team from Emory University at &lt;a href=&quot;http://flashpoint.gatech.edu&quot;&gt;Flashpoint&lt;/a&gt;, a unique and efficacious mindset school and startup studio at Georgia Tech. Our team had 200+ conversations with scientists, physicians, industry professionals, investors, etc. We discovered pockets of startup activity relevant to medicine, but this fledgling ecosystem was disorganized. We also learned many people did not believe Atlanta has adequate culture, resources, and opportunities to enable successful outcomes in medical entrepreneurship, at least in comparison to San Francisco or Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to cohere the disparate components of our medicine + technology ecosystem. In spring 2014, I co-founded Forge with Evan McClure (an MD/MBA student then, who now works in executive life science recruiting and private equity) and Arash Harzand (a chief resident in internal medicine then, who is now a cardiologist and digital health researcher). We recruited a team, organized events, and met lots of new peoplewho shared our vision of making Atlanta a viable place for multidisciplinary biomediucal entrepreneurship not necessarily confined to the ivory tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fall 2014, Forge organized the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forgehealth.org/2014hackathonsummary.pdf&quot;&gt;first healthcare hackathon in Atlanta&lt;/a&gt; under the leadership of Kevin Olsen (now an anesthesiology resident). The success of this event followed months of well-attended events and continued sponsorship interest. We felt the scarcity of resources for medical startup founders was a problem we could help with. To better serve this goal, we incorporated as a non-profit organization with Arash at the helm. This enabled us to raise more money and market ourselves with transparency and credibility. We also created a Board of Directors to have access to, and oversight and advice from  leaders in academia, industry, and the investment community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now 2015 and Forge has new ideas, leaders, and partners. We will organize another hackathon, coding and design workshops, and evening networking events for founders, investors, and operators. We also have a new look, logo, and website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we must remain focused on signal over noise. Startups are a buzzword and every week there is a new meetup, group, or conference. When we organize events and initiatives, we ask if it is relevant to our focus: to seek people solving clinically meaningful projects with intellectually exciting technology, and to provide them with useful resources and a supportive community that did not previously exist in industry or academia alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Erik Reinertsen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Co-founder, Forge&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tips for new researchers</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/tips-for-new-researchers/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/tips-for-new-researchers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At UCLA, I did research as an undergraduate student for ~3 years. Here are some things I learned. This post is aimed towards undergraduate students but is relevant for healthcare professional students interested in research too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#terminology&quot;&gt;Terminology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tips&quot;&gt;General tips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#look&quot;&gt;What to look for in a lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#find&quot;&gt;How to find a lab position&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#good&quot;&gt;How to be a good researcher&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;terminology&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;terminology&quot;&gt;Terminology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principal Investigator&lt;/strong&gt; (usually just “PI”) - Professor who advises students, postdocs, staff, etc. They write grants and get the money required to fund such research. Also called “advisor”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Postdoc&lt;/strong&gt; - short for postdoctoral scholar or fellow, these are researchers who have an MD or PhD and are doing more research to prepare to become faculty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduate student&lt;/strong&gt; - a student doing their Masters degree or PhD. The latter entails classes, teaching, and most importantly performing research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellow&lt;/strong&gt; - in the context of a clinician, a Fellow has completed residency and is pursuing further subspecialty training. Many fellowships involve research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protected time / academic day&lt;/strong&gt; - time when the clinician does not have teaching or clinical duties and can work on research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R01&lt;/strong&gt; - grant provide by the NIH to support research; the financial lifeblood of much biomedical research. Increasingly competitive to win. Any lab with 1 or more R01s can be considered “well funded”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab meeting&lt;/strong&gt; - a meeting of the entire lab to update the PI on research progress, get input from everyone else, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal club&lt;/strong&gt; - a regular meeting where a researcher gives a presentation on a published paper (not their own), and critiques it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;tips&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-tips&quot;&gt;General tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You aren’t selling your soul. Try it out and see if you enjoy the endeavor upon which academia is built.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not expect to get paid in $ (unless you can commit an entire year, full time).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Here are some suggested outcomes to aim for:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;strong letter of recommendation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;abstracts &amp;amp; posters, publication(s)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;firsthand understanding of the chronic failure that is research&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;career-advancing relationships with academics&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2+ years of continual experience in the same group may improve your chance of publication and acquisition of useful skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;look&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-look-for-in-a-lab&quot;&gt;What to look for in a lab&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IMO mentoring environment of the lab is MUCH MORE important for your career success than how interesting you find the topic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/heydavemathews&quot;&gt;@heydavemathews&lt;/a&gt; has another view: the topic is important. Intrinsic meaning is rewarding, and therefore sustainable. Merely working to put in your dues is not. Dave says “does the work resonate with you? Is it intrinsically interesting to YOU? Being weirdly into it is healthy. and necessary.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The typical process of judging a lab is not objective. You will Google the PI, judge the lab based on appearance of lab website (like wine), and correlate the merit of their research with how many times the word “Nature” appears in their PubMed. This feels right but it is incorrect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To find a good work environment, talk to the PI and students instead of relying on Google
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ask the PI about their thoughts on mentoring, teaching, previous student outcomes, and lab organization.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;These are more important for you than the nebulous, political vanity metrics that most labs are judged on.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relevant metrics change once you are a grad student, fellow / postdoc, and eventual collaborator.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Everyone lies and embellishes, so talking to five people will let you establish an average assessment that should be closer to reality than what the PI alone claims.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask your “assigned faculty mentor”. At UCLA, faculty were forced to meet students 1:1 for 15 minutes. They can give you some suggestions of who to contact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lab size is not that important, because there are pros and cons to small and large labs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small lab / new PI:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;more attention with PI, closer relationships between lab members&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;but drama is annoying, your PI may not be politically powerful, and lab may not be efficient because it is just establishing protocols&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large lab / established PI:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;more independence, more research $ for nicer equipment and supplies&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;but lab may be disorganized, and you have to fight for attention to make your accomplishments known to the faculty&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start working with a good senior undergraduate, or graduate student. Ideally someone who has published anything before.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transition to an independent project after a year or two.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faculty mentor fit is not as important now, especially if you have a good grad student mentor. The PI is more important once you are in grad school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;find&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-find-a-lab-position&quot;&gt;How to find a lab position&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you email faculty, do not expect rapid replies, or replies at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare for being rejected.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emails should be concise, organized, and specific.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your email subject should not say “Undergrad interested in research”. It should say “Sophomore BioE pre-PhD interested in 2-year lab research, starting immediately”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bad emails are long and redundantly polite:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Dear Professor Firstname Lastname, I am an undergraduate student majoring in X at University of Somewhere. I am writing to you to express my interest in potentially pursuing a research opportunity in your lab, which I came across via the department website. My future interests include …”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better emails direct and concise (yet still polite):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hi Dr. Lastname, I am a sophomore undergrad majoring in computational biology and would like to do research in your lab. Specifically, I am interested in X, Y, and Z. Attached is my CV. Please let me know if you are willing to meet in person. Thank you for your time!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The objective of your email is enable you to meet the PI in person, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be accepted right away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;good&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-be-a-good-researcher&quot;&gt;How to be a good researcher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/heydavemathews&quot;&gt;@heydavemathews&lt;/a&gt;: Work your ass off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Document everything you do. This is a resource for your lab’s future students. The PI will appreciate it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every other week, re-organize your documents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back everything up (Dropbox, Box, Time Machine)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electronically map your physical lab notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schedule regular meetings with people you must meet with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Treat lab meetings with more importance than your peers and rivals. They are the only chance you have to get on stage in front of your advisor, collaborators, etc. Make your presentation flawless&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge is power. If your PI gives you a paper, read it and three of the references / relevant papers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be a team player. Go out of your way to help lab mates with anything you can.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarify expectations with co-workers and mentors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pay it forward to mentor and help younger students. Every day you get one step closer to be being the boss. And you went through the same valley of ignorance they went through.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be a great single-tasker. You will be inefficient if you multi-task. If you are distracted and make mistakes at the bench, it could cost you hours to repeat the experiment (or months if you ruin rare samples).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People will make suggestions, and do things that you may find sub-optimal. Test those theories instead of blindly following advice that may be bad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PIs have earned the right to give advice because they have years of experience. It doesn’t make it correct though. I know thoughtless PIs who are inefficient and not very successful. I also know incredible faculty. Appreciate the range.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How I prepared for Step 1 of the USMLE</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/prep-for-step-1-usmle/"/>
   <updated>2014-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/prep-for-step-1-usmle</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources-i-recommend&quot;&gt;Resources I recommend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Aid 2013&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;USMLE-Rx qbank (hereby referred to as “rx”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;USMLE World qbank (hereby referred to as “uworld”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Picmonic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pathoma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources-i-do-not-recommend&quot;&gt;Resources I DO NOT recommend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microbio made ridiculously simple – I didn’t like the text-heavy format. I could have just read First Aid, used flashcards, and done questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emory-specific: every module textbook except for Lily cardiology (First Aid and Wikipedia are sufficient to understand pathophysiology) are a waste of money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goljan is too dense and comprehensive; use Pathoma instead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robbins &amp;amp; Cotran is even thicker than Goljan!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scheduling-emory-centric&quot;&gt;Scheduling (Emory-centric)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M2 ended on November 22nd, 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I took Step 1 on January 27th, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This gave me 65 days (9 weeks, 2 days) to prepare.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I took 8 days off to travel to California for a conference, see my family for the holidays, etc. This left me with 57 days (8 weeks, 1 day) to prepare.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Realistically, I studied 5 to 6 full days per week, and used 8 weeks. This was a perfect amount of time. Less would be insufficient, and more would leave me burnt out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To maintain balance and optimize long-term focus, I recommend regularly exercising, sleeping 6-8 hours a night, and maintaining some social activity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I divided my studying into &lt;em&gt;two phases&lt;/em&gt;: learning and question banks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1--learning-phase&quot;&gt;Phase 1 – Learning phase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;33 days (4 weeks, 5 days), from 11/23/2013 to 1/5/2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I reviewed First Aid 2013 cover to cover for a second time. This was not the first time, because I used First Aid 2013 as the framework from which I chose topics to focus my studies on during the modules. I chose to ignore our provided syllabi in lieu of material that was guaranteed to be high yield. I did not fail any module exams, and scored well on NBME exams. I highly recommend this. If I could go back, I would skip more lectures, study more First Aid, and do Rx or Firecracker as I went through M1 and M2.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each section took 2-4 days to complete.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read the material, then did module-specific Rx questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I chose to learn with Rx (not UWorld) because Rx ties directly to First Aid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I only finished 40% of Rx; the goal was the reinforce learning of concepts via vignettes, not completion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My strongest sections: GI, pulmonology, psych.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My weakest sections: microbiology, pharmacology, EBM (because we learned it so long ago), cardiology, neurology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wish I spent less time on Learning and more time on QBanks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2--qbanks-phase&quot;&gt;Phase 2 – QBanks phase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;22 days (3 weeks, 1 day), from 1/6/2014 to 1/27/2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every day, I did UWorld blocks of 46 questions on all random (every topic in First Aid) in tutorial mode.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I heavily annotated First Aid with colored pens and sticky notes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I left a dot next to the topic in First Aid so I would know which topics were heavily tested.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most common topics on UWorld were EBM, HIV, hepatitis, antiviral drugs, diabetes, psych drug side effects, P450 modulators, alpha and beta blockers, heart murmurs, IBD, … will update list later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I eventually switched from tutorial to timed, do a block or two, then review the answers later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At first, it took me a day (8 hours of studying) to answer and review two 46-question blocks. I averaged ~60%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I improved my speed to four 46-question blocks (if I focused hard). My average score improved to &amp;gt;70%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I finished all 2200+ UWorld questions a few days before I sat for Step 1. I then reviewed the questions I got wrong. I highly recommend this. Completion of a qbank builds confidence, even if retention is not 100%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I also took both UWorld diagnostic exams (blocks of 4 questions that give you a representative score). I am unsure if this was useful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;test-day&quot;&gt;Test day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I took Step 1 at a ProMetric center 20 minutes east of Atlanta, in Tucker, GA. I chose this location because I assumed a suburban area would have less traffic and easier parking than downtown Atlanta.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I took a practice NBME exam at the test center a few days before Step 1. This helped me get a feel for the parking, building layout, security process, and computer system layout. I highly recommend this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On test day, I brought water, coffee, banana bread graciously baked by an M3 friend, and mixed nuts with dried fruits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I took two blocks of 46 questions, then a 5-10 minute break. I paced my caffeine intake and maintained hydration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I always finished every medical school exam and qbank block with time to spare, so I never worried about pacing. I usually finished a 46-question 60-minute block in about 45 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No matter how well-prepared, you will become mentally fatigued after the 5th straight block of 46 questions. Slow down, stretch, take deep breaths, and stay focused.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Answer every single question; guessing carries no penalty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
