<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Erik Reinertsen</title>
  <id>http://m3xm.github.io</id>
  <link href="http://m3xm.github.io" />
  <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <updated>2014-07-18T16:42:34-04:00</updated>
  <rights>Copyright 2014, Erik Reinertsen</rights>
  <author>
    <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
  </author>
  
    <entry>
      <title>How to improve Quantified Care</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/07/2014-07-18-how-to-improve-quantified-care.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quantifiedcare.com/&quot;&gt;QuantifiedCare&lt;/a&gt; is a new startup from Johns Hopkins University. They are an online store for digital health devices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whether you are a physician, nurse, PA, home health care worker or any other clinician you can provide higher quality care by collecting more actionable and reimbursable data streams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this effort is exciting, the site lacks clarity and invites questions. A launch page should answer questions and de-risk the venture (like a good pitch).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I suggest four areas of improvement. The last area  may be outside of QC&#39;s target market, and stems from personal interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Culture change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical &amp;amp; clinical hurdles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenges for mHealth in developing countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thoughts on feedback:&lt;/strong&gt; Accept criticism and revise the product. Don&#39;t waste much time responding to the blog post, tweet, or email. Fixing a problem beats winning an online argument. The take-home message is that &lt;em&gt;they had a question.&lt;/em&gt; You &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; give investors any reasons to ask questions. Knowing how to answer hard questions is not helpful because they may not ask, and refuse to fund you. Questions in people&#39;s heads are more dangerous than questions in their mouths. You will never know the weaknesses they found, so you cannot improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feedback in academia is different than startups:&lt;/strong&gt; Part of academic training is learning how to respond to tough questions (which faculty are thinking of during your entire talk). However, working in academia is not an excuse to leave your material with room for many questions. Being good at answering hard questions is &quot;Heroic&quot; difficulty. Leaving faculty with little material from which to ask hard questions is &quot;Legendary&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We mean well with our criticism:&lt;/strong&gt; This is intended to be constructive criticism. We support this endeavor, respect the herculean effort required to launch a startup, and wish the founders only the best. Hopefully this is helpful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Business model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QC appears to be a storefront, or warehouse distributor for these devices. If so, they should act like a distributor and find partner hospitals or mobile care units who are willing to re-fit (presumably to lower costs) with these devices to beta-test in a real healthcare system. If one small clinic at Hopkins adopts these devices, runs a trial, and reports improved care and lowered costs, QC would have leverage to expand to a larger market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a hospital, mobile care unit, or global health unit wanted to adopt one of these devises, would they go though Quantified care, or straight to the deceive manufacturer to reduce cost?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QC mentions &quot;reimbursement&quot; as a core part of CARE, but there is no information about how and how easily this happens with each product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the guesswork out of which product to buy has value, but it is not clear to me what those selling points are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the target market? Early adopters who already believe in these devices and want to find the best ones, or all doctors, even those who are mid- and late-adopters? If it is the latter, we need more education beyond &quot;we offer these products.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Culture change&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting to this future will be painful. Healthcare is an entrenched bureaucratic system. To effect real change, you need a charismatic leader, an engaged populace, and hardworking supporters on all levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology adoption will not be enabled by one company or organization. It will come as a result of a cultural shift. mHealth and QC devices must evolve from being &quot;nice to haves&quot;, or &quot;fancy&quot; to &quot;essential&quot; for the practice of good medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cultural shift will come as the result of an ecosystem of changes. There will be foundations pushing for it, management organizations pushing for it, and individuals pushing for adoption, because of a focus on outcomes in care and on cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential upside, established brand name, and credibility for being early to the mHealth game (in medicine, not just the cliches of fitness wearables) is huge. However, to capitalize on that you need to play a huge part in three ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education of the people as to why this is important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying outcomes for using this technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disseminating best practices on how to use it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They need partnerships (the Bill and Melindas of the medtech world), there need to be case studies of use, and, I think importantly, there have to be systems put in place for the management of all this information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such idea: an excellent offering, in my opinion, that will ease transition to mHealth technologies and simultaneously draw in the user, is a free-to-use, integrated platform, that centralizes all the user&#39;s patient data drawn from these devices and apps, monitors it, and provides a dashboard. If this could integrate with EMRs, I think there is a winner. There is a parallel trend in education with LMSs (Learning Management Systems, essentially the electronic medical records of the education world), which every school now needs, and the biggest selling point is: which and how many apps does your LMS integrate with? In fact, the biggest startup in education right now (Clever, IK12 &#39;12 and YC &#39;13), is solving that problem and that problem alone: they build APIs to get app X&#39;s data into LMS Y&#39;s system. That&#39;s all they do. Perhaps that information management angle is another angle to consider in the ecosystem of mHealth adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Marketing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the name, description, and landing page, I didn&#39;t expect a &quot;store&quot; page. I expected information on what QC is, how I can use it, workflows, how it would improve my practice, how it integrates with existing technology and info management systems, and generally how it would benefit me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transition from landing page to &quot;store&quot; is somewhat rough for me: why a store? Why are you trying to sell me all these very different devices? Which are entry-level? Which are more sophisticated? Which are high-use? And most importantly, why is this wrist cuff better than the one I already have and use? Does the patient need their own? Does it enable me to get data without a patient being in-office? Does it alert me when/if critical signs arise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally I think the value prop of each product needs to be fleshed out, and the products categorized, rather than selling the value of being a &quot;quantified physician&quot; and buying all the devices. Right now the only selling point that jumps out at me is being hip and up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the products are to be sold in a system, I&#39;d like to see information and examples of how they are integrated and managed, and case studies of how others have used them. If doctors are anything like teachers, this will help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Technical &amp;amp; clinical hurdles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem I see is that you need patient by-in. Patients would have to perceive this device as a robust alternative to the current standard of care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;what happens when you get 10,000? Where and how does the data get stored, should it be stored, for how long, and who is responsible for managing it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How skilled is the user? Just because he&#39;s a doctor, doesn&#39;t mean he knows how to use all the equipment properly. (This is a key issue everywhere).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blood pressure cuff isn&#39;t going to work on pregnant women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who owns the data? What are they doing with it? Why should I trust them? What EMR are they using, and what does it connect to (siloed data?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Challenges for mHealth in developing countries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RE: developing/under-resourced environments-- this is interesting in that we face many of the same issues in education. With the recent edtech boom, there have been mass moves to make this technology (and training) available to all schools, not just the well-resourced ones. What has been effective there are grants, foundations, and partnerships with community organizations and hardware manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there grants available to hospitals, practitioners, or healthcare management orgs in rural and urban areas to staff this technology? Bill and Melinda as well as many private firms sponsor these in ed. Further, are there discounts available for purchase in bulk? Apple, Google, and Microsoft all do this for iPads, Chromebooks, and tablets respectively. On occasion, teachers even band together (as part of an org) to purchase and get the discount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$2000 for those devices - that&#39;s a lot of gadget money to spend to collect the same vitals I can do for &amp;lt; $100 from CVS ...&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/07/2014-07-18-how-to-improve-quantified-care.html</id>
      <updated>2014-07-18T13:04:41-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Software Setup</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/07/2014-07-31-software-setup.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Terminal tools:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://totalterminal.binaryage.com/&quot;&gt;TotalTerminal&lt;/a&gt;: TotalTerminal is a plugin for Terminal.app. It provides persistent Visor Window which slides down when you press a hot-key. Courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/jgmalcolm&quot;&gt;@jgmalcolm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://toddwerth.com/2008/01/25/a-black-os-x-leopard-terminal-theme-that-is-actually-readable/&quot;&gt;IR_Blank&lt;/a&gt;: a black OS X terminal theme with colors to improve readability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ethanschoonover.com/solarized&quot;&gt;Solarized&lt;/a&gt;: a sixteen color palette (eight monotones, eight accent colors) designed for use with terminal and gui applications. Courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/yapatel525&quot;&gt;@yapatel525&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Text editors:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;a href=&quot;http://textwrangler.onfreedownload.com/?lp=adwords&amp;amp;tg=us&amp;amp;kw=Textwrangler&amp;amp;mt=e&amp;amp;ad=33478421933&amp;amp;pl=&amp;amp;ds=s&amp;amp;os=mac&amp;amp;gclid=Cj0KEQjw_42eBRDHqcG1psmtneEBEiQAWPL8WBo7Uq6d-vLeNCi9sQGfVDzBIEOfpm7gNDtCywptV-AaAg8U8P8HAQ&quot;&gt;Text Wrangler&lt;/a&gt;: A general-purpose text editor for light-duty composition, data-file editing, and manipulation of text-oriented data.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/07/2014-07-31-software-setup.html</id>
      <updated>2014-07-18T11:21:25-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Tips for new undergraduate researchers</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/07/tips-for-undergrad-researchers.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;General things to think about before diving in:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You aren&#39;t selling your soul. Try it out and see if you enjoy the endeavor upon which academia is built.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearly understand outcome metrics that define a productive research experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not expect to get paid in $&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideal outcomes:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strong letter of recommendation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;abstracts &amp;amp; posters, publication(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;experience (== firsthand understanding of the chronically dark &amp;amp; painful failure that is research)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relationships with faculty (you may come back to that institution for your next career move)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want 2-3 years of continual experience in the same group. This may improve your chance of publication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What to look for (specific)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mentoring environment of the lab is MUCH MORE important for your career success than how interesting you find the topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/heydavemathews&quot;&gt;@heydavemathews&lt;/a&gt; has another view: the topic is important. Intrinsic meaning is rewarding, and therefore sustainable. Merely working to put in your dues is not. Dave says &quot;does the work resonate with you? Is it intrinsically interesting to YOU? Being weirdly into it is healthy. and necessary.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The typical process of judging a lab is not objective. You will Google the PI, judge the lab based on appearance of lab website (like wine), and correlate the merit of their research with how many times the word “Nature” appears in their PubMed. This feels right but it is incorrect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To find a good work environment, talk to the PI and students instead of relying on Google

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask the PI about their thoughts on mentoring, teaching, previous student outcomes, and lab organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These are more important for you than the nebulous, political vanity metrics that most labs are judged on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relevant metrics change once you are a grad student, fellow / postdoc, and eventual collaborator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone lies and embellishes, so talking to five people will let you establish an average assessment that should be closer to reality than what the PI alone claims.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You won’t find the best research mentors teaching your lower division courses. These faculty either enjoy teaching more than research, or have been forced to teach by their chair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong researchers in specialized fields teach upper division courses, or graduate / medical courses, or nothing at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask your “assigned faculty mentor”. At UCLA, faculty were forced to meet students 1:1 for 15 minutes. They can give you some suggestions of who to contact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lab size is not that important, because there are pros and cons to small and large labs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small lab / new PI:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more attention with PI, closer relationships between lab members&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but drama is annoying, your PI may not be politically powerful, and lab may not be efficient because it is just establishing protocols&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large lab / established PI:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more independence, more research $ for nicer equipment and supplies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but lab may be disorganized, and you have to fight for attention to make your accomplishments known to the faculty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start working with a good senior undergraduate, or graduate student. Ideally someone who has published anything before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transition to an independent project after a year or two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faculty mentor fit is not as important now, especially if you have a good grad student mentor. The PI is more important once you are in grad school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How to look for a lab position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you email faculty, expect failure. Many professors will not email you back. Of those that do, some will reject you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails should be concise &amp;amp; specific&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your email subject should not say “Undergrad interested in research”. It should say “Sophomore BioE pre-PhD interested in 2-year lab research, starting immediately”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad email == obtuse, redundantly polite: “Dear Professor Firstname Lastname, I am writing to you to express my interest in potentially pursuing a research opportunity. I have Y years of experience in high school doing Z. My future interests include Q. etc… and it goes on for 4 paragraphs”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better email == direct, concise: “Dr. Lastname, I would like to meet you and discuss doing research in your lab. I am interested in X, Y, and Z. Attached is my CV. Please let me know if you have time to meet next week.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;How to be a good researcher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/heydavemathews&quot;&gt;@heydavemathews&lt;/a&gt;: Work your ass off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document everything you do. This is a resource for your lab&#39;s future students. The PI will appreciate it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every other week, re-organize your documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back everything up (Dropbox, Box, Time Machine)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electronically map your physical lab notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schedule regular meetings with people you must meet with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat lab meetings with more importance than your peers and rivals. They are the only chance you have to get on stage in front of your advisor, collaborators, etc. Make your presentation flawless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge is power. If your PI gives you a paper, read it and three of the references / relevant papers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a team player. Go out of your way to help lab mates with anything you can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarify expectations with co-workers and mentors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay it forward to mentor and help younger students. Every day you get one step closer to be being the boss. And you went through the same valley of ignorance they went through.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a great single-tasker. You will be inefficient if you multi-task. You will be tempted to multi-task because you have coursework and volunteer crap to do. Don’t. Turn off your phone. Don’t think about your upcoming exam while you are working at the bench. It is less efficient than pure study in the library, and you may mess something up at the bench and cost yourself more time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be aware of the context in which you work, and who you learn from.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you think you are above average, then by definition most of your peers (or even the students / grads ahead of you) are below your level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are actually above average, you will know what you don’t know, and work to improve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are at or below average, you will lack the ability to realize this, and you will think you are average or above average&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regardless, carefully look around you and learn from both victories and defeats of others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People will make suggestions, and do things that you may find sub-optimal. So test those theories instead of blindly following advice that may be bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PIs have earned the right to give advice because they have years of experience. It doesn’t make it correct though. I know some thoughtless PIs who are very inefficient. I also know incredible faculty who nobody else can emulate. Appreciate the range.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/07/tips-for-undergrad-researchers.html</id>
      <updated>2014-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Planning fallacy</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/06/planning-fallacy.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The planning fallacy is a tendency for people and organizations to underestimate how long they will need to complete a task, even when they have experience of similar tasks over-running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forgeatl.com&quot;&gt;Forge&lt;/a&gt; is planning the first-ever Healthcare Hackathon in Atlanta. Our first estimate of the budget was originally $20,000. The numbers seemed sound, and our estimates felt accurate. But making economic decisions off of &quot;feelings&quot; is dangerous. Having read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Thinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman/dp/0374533555/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1402674266&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=thinking+fast+and+slow&quot;&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/a&gt;, I realized we were probably committing the &lt;em&gt;planning fallacy&lt;/em&gt;. I immediately increased our total budget request by 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Historical precedent, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Kahneman&quot;&gt;Daniel Kahneman&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s outstanding book:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In July 1997, the proposed new Scottish Parliament building was estimated to cost up to £40 mil. By 1999, the budget was £109 mil. In April, legislators imposed a £195 mil. camp on costs. By 2001, the cost rose to 241. The story continues... the building was eventually completed in 2004 for £431 mil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 90% of railway projects between 1969 and 1998, the number of passengers projected to use the system was overestimated, and the average cost overrun was 45%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2002, a survey of American homeowners who had remodeled their kitchen found on average they expected to pay $19,000. They ended up paying an average of $38,769.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To mitigate the planning fallacy, you can do three things:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify a reference class (e.g. UCLA and Stanford Hackathons)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obtain enough info from those event planners to make a baseline cost prediction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjust the prediction based on the specifics of our case (several experienced event planners in Atlanta told me to expect cost overruns above what we calculated)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As planning progressed, our budget rose to $50,000, or 2.5x our original estimate. But things are looking good. We are incredibly excited to host this Hackathon, and the learning experience has been invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/06/planning-fallacy.html</id>
      <updated>2014-06-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Fixing the NRMP match 2</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/06/fixing-the-match-2.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rohan Jotwani (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/almostdoc_ro&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@almostdoc_ro&lt;/a&gt;), an MD/MBA Candidate at the Tufts School of Medicine, posted a great response on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medstro.com/posts/808&quot;&gt;Medstro&lt;/a&gt; to my &lt;a href=&quot;http://erikreinertsen.github.io/2014/05/fixingthematch.html&quot;&gt;original post about &quot;fixing the match&quot;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I respectfully disagree with some points made in the article, although the article is very well-written and thought-provoking. Within the context that we are currently facing a shortage of physicians and the gap will widen in the future, &lt;strong&gt;I think the solution lies in increasing the number of residency spots/federal funding for GME&lt;/strong&gt; (check out &lt;a href=&quot;savegme.org&quot;&gt;savegme.org&lt;/a&gt; for more data on this) and potentially breaking up certain specialities&#39; monopoly over capped spots, not decreasing the number of medical school spots overall. I also think it wouldn&#39;t matter if we limited med school admissions anyway because folks would turn to foreign medical schools, which would likely welcome more candidates, given their business model. Also, I think &lt;strong&gt;having the algorithm weed out certain applicants based on their numerical stats for the competitive residencies robs our medical system of physicians that offer traits which can&#39;t be quantified into an algorithm.&lt;/strong&gt; Hopefully most of us would agree that standardized tests are not a perfect indication of future potential in just about any profession and giving more power to it is the opposite approach I would take to fixing the NRMP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Here&#39;s my response:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rohan, you make some strong points. Numbers don&#39;t lie, although the forces shaping their evolution may not be transparent or understandable. Increasing federal funding for GME would likely help, but it inevitably leads to the question of where this extra funding comes from, and healthcare spending as a whole. I don&#39;t know much about this topic though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To elaborate on a point I made in my blog post (but perhaps not explicitly), I hypothesize some dissatisfaction with the NRMP stems from a mismatch between expectations and reality. The underlying problem is having more applicants than spots. I agree that the # of foreign medical graduates would probably increase in response to decreased US medical school slots, but it is reasonable to think this would increase the fraction of US medical school graduates who successfully match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weeding out applicants: decades of research suggests objective data should trump non-quantifiable traits if the goal is to predict future performance. I strongly recommend Daniel Kahneman&#39;s work, which, as an MD/MBA you should find both fascinating and relevant. For most scenarios, simple correlative algorithms utilizing objective data are actually superior predictors of complex phenomena (especially longitudinal, i.e. 5-year survival) compared to multicomponent models or expert review. In fact, when experts modify simple algorithms based on their subjective experience, predictive accuracy often declines due to cognitive bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I agree with you - standardized tests such as our board exams are far from perfect. An objectively superior (but rather disliked) approach is the MMI, which spreads subjective bias among several observers. Let me elaborate: when I say &quot;numerical stats&quot;, I don&#39;t mean board scores and GPA. I refer to a consistent and objective method of assessing scholarly productivity, professionalism, perseverance, social interaction. This system has yet to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we both agree there exist several domains that are not captured in exam scores that may be predictive for future performance in medicine. This challenge is not unique to the NMRP, and extends to all of medical education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original article by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/amyfaithho&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@amyfaithho&lt;/a&gt; which spurred this interesting conversation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/theapothecary/2014/04/15/how-a-nobel-economist-ruined-the-residency-matching-system-for-newly-minted-m-d-s/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What do you think about the residency match process? How can we make it better? Tweet / blog about it!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/06/fixing-the-match-2.html</id>
      <updated>2014-06-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Forge Salon 3</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/salon-3.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forgeatl.com&quot;&gt;Forge&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; 3rd Salon took place at Technology Enterprise Park. Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://storify.com/ForgeATL/salon-3&quot;&gt;Storify&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians are frustrated by problems that require technological solutions. Engineers, entrepreneurs, and makers build cool stuff, but have no clue what problems are clinically relevant. Finally, it can be difficult to get all of these people in the same room at
the same time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Salons fix these problems in three key ways:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We highlight local innovation resources, centers, and institutions. At Salon 3, the VP of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sjm.com/cardiomems&quot;&gt;CardioMEMS&lt;/a&gt; gave a guest talk about his work.
CardioMEMS was recently acquired by St. Jude Medical with an up-front investment of $60M and the exclusive option of acquiring the company
for an additional $375M given the completion of certain commercialization milestones. Read more about it &lt;a href=&quot;http://jaycaplan.com/2010/09/14/cardiomems-an-earn-out-with-a-twist/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinicians share unmet challenges in medicine and healthcare over 5-minute talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Engineers, entrepreneurs, and makers share cool new technologies over 5-minute talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Attendees always have a great time networking after the talks. If you show up, be sure to bring a full stack of business cards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you are interested in learning more, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:emily@forgeatl.com&quot;&gt;Emily Brayman&lt;/a&gt;, our Salon Director.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/salon-3.html</id>
      <updated>2014-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Announcing the 1st Life Sciences I-Corps Program at GaTech</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/icorps-lifescience.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Are you a student or faculty member in healthcare or the life sciences interested in commercializing your technology? This Fall, get ready to apply for a Life Sciences Regional I-Corps Program at Georgia Tech, organized by your friendly neighborhood VentureLab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last December I attended the final pitches of UCSF’s Lean Launchpad for Life Sciences &amp;amp; Healthcare, run by Steve Blank. I was blown away by how much progress the teams made in just a few weeks. The evening reinforced my belief that customer discovery, business acumen, and entrepreneurial spirit could transform innovation in academic medicine. My new mission was clear: to bring the Lean LaunchPad for Life Sciences back to Atlanta, where we have amazing substrate for medical innovation with Emory &amp;amp; Georgia Tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend Jenny, a postdoctoral fellow and entrepreneur in the course, helped me snag Steve’s phone number. I called him, explained how awesome the Lean Launchpad concept was, and shared how Atlanta was perfect for it. His response – “Yeah, let’s do it! Let me know how I can help” – was refreshing, and so … Silicon Valley. I was used to academic administrators and faculty telling me reasons why my idea was not feasible. He directed me to Keith McGreggor, director of GT’s VentureLab and NSF iCorps instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a chat with Harold Solomon (friend, mentor, and Forge supporter), as well as Ravi Bellamkonda, Professor and Chair of BME at Georgia Tech. Everyone loved the idea. In fact, they were already considering something similar, given the explosion of entrepreneurial interest in healthcare. Actually, I didn’t do much except remind them how awesome this could be. And now it’s happening this fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sept 10, 11, 12: 7 am - 9 pm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sept 16, 23, 30, October 7, 14, 21: 11 am – 5 pm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October 28, 29: 7am – 6pm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need three people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entrepreneurial lead – usually a student&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business mentor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:brandy.nagel@venturelab.gatech.edu&quot;&gt;Brandy Nagel&lt;/a&gt; to learn more.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More updates soon!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/icorps-lifescience.html</id>
      <updated>2014-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Fixing the NRMP match</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/fixing-the-match.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Amy Ho outlined the flaws of the NMRP match. Her bottom line is pointed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This system is highly wasteful. It incurs massive costs for hospitals and students through the interview process, precludes contract negotiations that could optimize value for both parties and results in depressed wages for young physicians. Additionally, it incurs significant opportunity cost in trading interviews for educational senior year curricula, causes undue duress for applicants and their families and contributes to decreased quality of care in physicians unsatisfied with results of the Match.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While her argument is compelling, I want to add some thoughts geared towards solutions. I believe technology offers tangible ways to improve these problems. I encourage readers to think of how they would tackle these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let’s go:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medical education today is nothing like it was 60 years ago. Today, many specialties have more US medical graduates than residency positions, and international medical graduates and physicians reapplying for residency also compete in the match. Medical schools continue to increase, as have the birth of osteopathic schools and Caribbean schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oversimplified solution: cut the number of students accepted to medical school and reduce medical school class size. Medical student tuition does not contribute to the majority of academic medical center income. I don’t have a citation handy, but I think the majority of funding is actually research-oriented. Anyways, Johns Hopkins is tightening the belt on PhD programs. Academic science suffers a similar but not fully congruent problem; there are too many PhDs doing multiple postdocs who cannot find faculty positions. The solution is economically obvious, but socially and mechanistically challenging:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This year, 5.6% of US allopathic (MD) seniors did not match, and 22.3% of US osteopathic (DO) seniors did not match. On the whole, 25.0% of applicants in the NRMP Match did not match – with a 25% unemployment rate, how successful is the Match, really?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suggests the match algorithm is not robust. I would need to know more about the overall data for unmatched applicants. My understanding is these applicants tend to apply to highly competitive specialities like dermatology, plastic surgery, and urology – with unrealistic expectations and less than competitive applications.The system should incorporate safeguards based on objective, historical information. For example, say 95% (or 99% or 99.9%) of applicants with a Step 1 score of X, Step 2 score of Y, overall grades of Z, and Q number of publications do not match in neurosurgery. The system should simply not allow that applicant to apply to that specialty. Other metrics such as type of school and degree (MD, DO, dual degree, US, foreign) could be incorporated in a regression analysis model that profiles applicants, and compares them to profiles of successful candidates at different programs for different specialties. Some might find this too harsh; perhaps the system can merely warn applicants if they are truly not competitive for a given program before they pour time and money down the drain. Analogy: if Tinder warned you that you were too ugly, it could save everyone time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;With a 15% tax rate, $7,470.76 becomes $8,789.13 in pre-tax income. With 34,270 active applicants in the Match in 2014, $302 million is wasted annually, in the setting of tight graduate medical education funding, increasing student debt and decreasing physician reimbursement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an engineer, I respect these back-of-the envelope calculations. Let me try my own. The average debt of indebted MD graduates of the class of 2013 was $169,901. $8,789.13 is %5.2 of overall medical school debt, which is a small overall fraction. My classmates love eating at nice restaurants such as the Spence, buying expensive clothes, and watching 3D Imax movies instead of illegally bittorrenting. To them, debt is debt. However, $300 million cumulatively is nothing to sneeze at. Be that as it may, a world without a match would still require interviews and travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solution: coordinate group travel, housing, and meals to save tremendous costs. Divide interviews into a quarter system and organize regionally. Usually, this is left to the applicants, and few programs actively coordinate with each other to save students money and time. But vacation-planning services are already abundant online. One plane ticket to the West Coast, with shared housing and ground transportation among several candidates, could knock out 3-5 interviews for the price of 1-2 “typical” interviews done separately. In the first quarter, 25% of applicants interview in the West region, 25% in the Northeast, 25% in the Southeast, and 25% in the NW and Midwest. In the second quarter, the applicant pool rotates to the next region. You might think it sounds insane to use software to force people to decide where to go, when. Oh, wait. Actually, all this does is formalize what already happens but in a more efficient and controlled manner. The challenge lies in aligning incentives. Med students save money, while NRMP and residency programs spend it to make this happen. That is a critical challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dual degrees (MD/JD, MD/MBA, MD/MPH) are ever-increasing and many applicants will bring additional value to their hospital&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not see data to support this claim, but I also lack any data to support a counter-argument. I can see how MD/MBAs in executive positions might bring $ value through enacting economically beneficial policies / financial restructuring, and how the other dual-degrees bring insight from different fields. However, this value is hard to quantify in dollars. I do know that MD/PhDs in academic faculty positions that focus on research or trained in a “cognitive” or diagnostic specialty make less income in salary than their counterparts who only have MDs and perform procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the Match translates into thousands of physicians training in an undesired specialty, in an undesired city and in an undesired situation split from their families. These physicians, lives forced by the Match, cannot be assumed to perform at the same quality as those that matched into their ‘dream job’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of this population, do they end up leaving the profession prematurely?  Are their career trajectories as successful? Are their satisfaction rates the same? What about their suicide rates, addiction rates and wellness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues suggest profoundly important topics of research. If we can’t find the results of these studies today online, they need to be done soon. To motivate change in policy, we need data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This topic demands insight from thinkers who possess a rigorous understanding of behavioral economics, finance, and systems engineering. But I also think it demands attention from everyone else, especially from rising young physicians who will inherit positions of authority, and the responsibility to enact meaningful change more than any other stakeholder.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/fixing-the-match.html</id>
      <updated>2014-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>How to commercialize technology in academia</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/commercializing-tech-in-academia.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The American Physician Scientists Association 10th annual meeting featured a Policy Panel with leaders in device development, entrepreneurship, and FDA/governmental oversight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin Burke, DO&lt;/strong&gt; - Professor of Medicine and Director of the Heart Rhythm Center, University of Chicago&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larissa Lapteva, MD, MHS&lt;/strong&gt; – Medical Officer, Rare Diseases Program, Office of New Drugs, CDER, FDA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lex Van Der Ploeg, PhD&lt;/strong&gt; – Chief Science Officer, Rhythm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I asked the following question via Facebook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What can academic institutions do to encourage a culture of technology commercialization? How can students explore these opportunities while still honing rigorous basic science skills during their PhD?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panelists answered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin Burke:&lt;/strong&gt; Training investigators to be able to effectively communicate the idea to those in the technology transfer office at their institution and be able to negotiate the next steps. However, there is often difficulty in developing personal relationships with those working in the technology transfer office due to high turnover rate. The easiest route to more familiarize oneself is through a mentor who has significant experience dealing with technology transfer, whether that is your own mentor or finding someone outside of your immediate laboratory personnel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lex Van Der Ploeg:&lt;/strong&gt; Thinking ahead about how to develop a product while doing the research. One way is through mentoring from the technology transfer office, which can be achieved by asking them to be involved in your research team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larissa Laptera:&lt;/strong&gt; At the governmental policy level, try to promote collaborations between researchers, technology transfer businesses, and industry for pre-competitive space that focuses on outcomes and endpoints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Student Thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider working with your graduate student body leadership to advocate for a research commercialization course, where they can cover topics such as the process of getting a patent submitted to when it is approved, negotiations, what the technology transfer will need from you, and how they can be involved early in the research process in terms of considerations you need when designing experiments so if results are positive they can be taken to the next step more easily. This has been achieved at the University of Nebraska Medical Center (UNMC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider asking your technology transfer office to link with bioscience business programs that offer seminars and webinars where students can earn a certificate after participating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider asking a faculty with significant experience dealing with technology transfer to be on your thesis committee and specifically ask them to provide that perspective regarding the design and implementation of your experiments and extracurriculars available locally and nationally to become more familiar with the technology transfer process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many technology transfer offices hire postdocs and so consider talking with them to learn more about the kind of work they do and the internship possibilities during and right after graduate school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/05/commercializing-tech-in-academia.html</id>
      <updated>2014-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Five lessons from Silicon Valley for academic medicine</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/04/5-lessons-from-silicon-valley.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Advances in technology, ranging from vaccines to MRI, have always driven the greatest revolutions in healthcare. Progress in molecularly targeted therapeutics, silencing RNA, and gene therapy is promising, but digital health is perhaps the fastest growing frontier in medicine. In 2013, digital health funding rose more than 39%, exceeding $1.9B with 195 venture deals ($2M+). However, this rapid growth is from tech diffusing into medicine, and not the other way around. Clinicians continue to use antiquated electronic medical record (EMR) systems with clunky interfaces on ten-year old Dell desktops. Why is medicine so slow to change, especially in academia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is that physicians are not trained to innovate. Memorizing protocols, doses, and clinical signs are arguably more useful for everyday practice on the wards compared to exercising immense creativity. In fact, creativity can potentially harm patients. Suppose a statistically powered trial suggests a treatment improves outcomes. Objective data should trump individual preference and creativity at the point of care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, physicians are not totally non-innovative. Academic clinicians advance clinical care through new knowledge. Research intends to translate creative questions into useful answers about diagnosis and treatment. Furthermore, senior physicians often deviate from evidence-based treatment guidelines based on their experience, but the privilege of creativity must be earned after decades of experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academic scientists also struggle to efficiently innovate. Translating inventions from the lab to the market is notoriously complex and slow in the university setting. Offices of technology transfer earn poor reputations due to inept staff and leadership that lack genuine startup experience. Universities – especially small- and mid-size institutions – may lack strong role models on the faculty who have achieved both academic and commercial success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This latter issue highlights one of the most dangerous cultural barriers to innovation in academia: the misalignment between activities which advance technology innovation, and those which further academic careers. Basic science departments may look more favorably upon a publication in a reputable journal versus a filed patent, or the successful raising of seed funding for a startup. Fortunately, the perception of technology innovation is becoming more positive in academia. These ethical, cultural, and institutional issues in academia stand in stark difference to Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silicon Valley is home to many of the world’s largest technology corporations, as well as thousands of small startups. Ever since HP and Apple started in a garage, countless other entrepreneurs have adopted the belief that anything is possible, and anyone can change the world with their idea. Furthermore, the immense financial success of tech companies in Silicon Valley has fueled an innovation cycle by attracting investors and more visionary entrepreneurs. The drive, excitement, marathon work ethic, and intensity of startup culture is at first glance comparable to medicine, but there are far more billion-dollar deals and TED-talk meetups in Palo Alto than any hospital. What makes this place so special? Accenture recently published a report where they found the workplace culture of Silicon Valley consists of &lt;em&gt;five seemingly contradictory characteristics&lt;/em&gt; that have helped the region produce life-changing innovations and many of the world’s most successful companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laid back – yet driven for speed.&lt;/strong&gt; Congenial and laid-back, people will nevertheless work intensely for long hours for their companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Committed – yet independent.&lt;/strong&gt; People are deeply committed to their work and their colleagues. Yet they are essentially “free agents” with no strong allegiance to one company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitive – yet cooperative.&lt;/strong&gt; Companies and individuals can be ruthless competitors. But they also cooperate regularly toward larger goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pragmatic – yet optimistic.&lt;/strong&gt; People realize that failures are inevitable. But they are also optimistic that any problem can eventually be solved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extrinsically motivated – yet intrinsically fulfilled.&lt;/strong&gt; People are motivated by money. However, their fulfillment comes from being recognized for their creativity and innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In parallel with these characteristics, I present five suggestions in which leaders could improve academic culture, efficiency, and innovation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speed up decision-making and eliminate bureaucracy.&lt;/strong&gt; Quick, agile decision-making instead of slow, methodical consensus-building will allow leaders to test hypotheses, learn about their organizations, and act swiftly. Tolerate zero bureaucracy if it hinders progress in areas that do not absolutely demand red tape. Clinical trials and patient safety require regulation, but making a new departmental website should take &amp;lt;24 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brand the institution as the people in it, and what they do.&lt;/strong&gt; If people value their work and colleagues more than the company, the organization has a fundamental identity crisis. University X is considered great not because it is an institution. It is great because of the people in it, and what they do. Make this a clear part of the culture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourage “coopetition” by rewarding people with institutional wins.&lt;/strong&gt; Compensate employees with “virtual stock options” or institutionally available amenities. People should compete for personal benefit, yet realize their compensation depends on the success of their department or institution as a whole. Publicly recognize wins from faculty, staff, and students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take controlled risks, and embrace learning from failure.&lt;/strong&gt; Failing, and failing fast, are a huge part of the culture. The VC community often backs entrepreneurs who have a history of failed businesses. Obviously, one does not seek failure in the setting of a life-saving operation. But academia should invest more in high-risk high-reward research and commercial ventures. Laboratory investigators often lack formal management training, and should thus work with or learn from professionals experienced in project management. Academic projects should incorporate faster cycle times, metrics acquisition, and learning from failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make academia a meritocracy.&lt;/strong&gt; In Silicon Valley, people who are smart, talented, and work insanely hard will get ahead. Chris DiGiorgio notes that “in the Valley, your pedigree – family status, university or socioeconomic class – matters a lot less than your abilities, accomplishments and what you can contribute to the company. Academia should reward high-potential individuals with resources, authority, and compensation appropriate for their contributions, regardless of academic rank or standing. Firing bureaucrats who slow progress will improve work culture for all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While academic culture will take time to modernize, we can already start fostering the “startup spirit” among innovators
interested in medical technology and healthcare. Earlier this year, my colleagues and I founded &lt;a href=&quot;www.forgeatl.com&quot;&gt;Forge&lt;/a&gt;.
We connect clinicians, engineers, business professionals, and students to accelerate development of healthcare startups.
This year, we have contributed to Atlanta&#39;s innovation culture by hosting hackathons, meetups, and pitch competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I believe creating a successful startup culture in Atlanta will empower more people to advance healthcare innovation!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tecco, H. 2013 Digital Health Funding Report. Rock Health 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harris, J. G. &amp;amp; Junglas, I. Decoding the Contradictory Culture of Silicon Valley. Accenture 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/04/5-lessons-from-silicon-valley.html</id>
      <updated>2014-04-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>How I prepared for Step 1 of the USMLE</title>
      <link href="http://m3xm.github.io/2014/01/step1-usmle.html" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Resources I recommend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First Aid 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USMLE-Rx qbank (hereby referred to as “rx”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USMLE World qbank (hereby referred to as “uworld”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Picmonic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pathoma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Resources I DO NOT recommend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microbio made ridiculously simple – I didn’t like the text-heavy format. I could have just read First Aid, used flashcards, and done questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emory-specific: every module textbook except for Lily cardiology (First Aid and Wikipedia are sufficient to understand pathophysiology) are a waste of money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goljan is too dense and comprehensive; use Pathoma instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robbins &amp;amp; Cotran is even thicker than Goljan!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Scheduling (Emory-centric)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M2 ended on November 22nd, 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took Step 1 on January 27th, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This gave me 65 days (9 weeks, 2 days) to prepare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took 8 days off to travel to California for a conference, see my family for the holidays, etc. This left me with 57 days (8 weeks, 1 day) to prepare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistically, I studied 5 to 6 full days per week, and used 8 weeks. This was a perfect amount of time. Less would be insufficient, and more would leave me burnt out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To maintain balance and optimize long-term focus, I recommend regularly exercising, sleeping 6-8 hours a night, and maintaining some social activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I divided my studying into &lt;em&gt;two phases&lt;/em&gt;: learning and question banks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;1 – Learning phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;33 days (4 weeks, 5 days), from 11/23/2013 to 1/5/2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I reviewed First Aid 2013 cover to cover for a second time. This was not the first time, because I used First Aid 2013 as the framework from which I chose topics to focus my studies on during the modules. I chose to ignore our provided syllabi in lieu of material that was guaranteed to be high yield. I did not fail any module exams, and scored well on NBME exams. I highly recommend this. If I could go back, I would skip more lectures, study more First Aid, and do Rx or Firecracker as I went through M1 and M2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each section took 2-4 days to complete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I read the material, then did module-specific Rx questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I chose to learn with Rx (not UWorld) because Rx ties directly to First Aid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I only finished 40% of Rx; the goal was the reinforce learning of concepts via vignettes, not completion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My strongest sections: GI, pulmonology, psych.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My weakest sections: microbiology, pharmacology, EBM (because we learned it so long ago), cardiology, neurology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wish I spent less time on Learning and more time on QBanks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;2 – QBanks phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22 days (3 weeks, 1 day), from 1/6/2014 to 1/27/2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every day, I did UWorld blocks of 46 questions on all random (every topic in First Aid) in tutorial mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I heavily annotated First Aid with colored pens and sticky notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I left a dot next to the topic in First Aid so I would know which topics were heavily tested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most common topics on UWorld were EBM, HIV, hepatitis, antiviral drugs, diabetes, psych drug side effects, P450 modulators, alpha and beta blockers, heart murmurs, IBD, … will update list later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I eventually switched from tutorial to timed, do a block or two, then review the answers later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At first, it took me a day (8 hours of studying) to answer and review two 46-question blocks. I averaged ~60%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I improved my speed to four 46-question blocks (if I focused hard). My average score improved to &gt;70%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finished all 2200+ UWorld questions a few days before I sat for Step 1. I then reviewed the questions I got wrong. I highly recommend this. Completion of a qbank builds confidence, even if retention is not 100%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also took both UWorld diagnostic exams (blocks of 4 questions that give you a representative score). I am unsure if this was useful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Test day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took Step 1 at a ProMetric center 20 minutes east of Atlanta, in Tucker, GA. I chose this location because I assumed a suburban area would have less traffic and easier parking than downtown Atlanta.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took a practice NBME exam at the test center a few days before Step 1. This helped me get a feel for the parking, building layout, security process, and computer system layout. I highly recommend this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On test day, I brought water, canned espresso, and snacks with complex carbohydrates and protein (banana bread graciously baked by an M3 friend, and mixed nuts with dried fruits).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took two blocks of 46 questions, then a 5-10 minute break. I paced my caffeine intake and maintained hydration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I always finished every medical school exam and qbank block with time to spare, so I never worried about pacing. I usually finished a 46-question 60-minute block in about 45 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No matter how well-prepared, you will become mentally fatigued after the 5th straight block of 46 questions. Slow down, stretch, take deep breaths, and stay focused.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not forget to answer every single question, because guessing carries no penalty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Useful links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USMLE score correlations: table correlating UWorld to USMLE scores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</summary>
      <id>http://m3xm.github.io/2014/01/step1-usmle.html</id>
      <updated>2014-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Erik Reinertsen</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
</feed>
